<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A frutefull and godly exposition and declaracion of the kyngdom of Christ and of the christen lybertye, made vpo[n] the wordes of the prophete Jeremye in the xxij. chapter, with an exposycyon of the viij. Psalme, intreatyng of the same matter, by the famous clerke Doctor Martyn Luther, whereunto is annexed A godly sermon, of Doctor Urbanus Regius, vpon the ix. Chapyter of Mathewe of the woman that had an issew of blood &amp; of the rulers daughter, newly translated oute of hyghe Almayne.</title>
            <title>Epistel aus dem Propheten Jeremia. English</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103978</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839720</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839720</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 848:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A frutefull and godly exposition and declaracion of the kyngdom of Christ and of the christen lybertye, made vpo[n] the wordes of the prophete Jeremye in the xxij. chapter, with an exposycyon of the viij. Psalme, intreatyng of the same matter, by the famous clerke Doctor Martyn Luther, whereunto is annexed A godly sermon, of Doctor Urbanus Regius, vpon the ix. Chapyter of Mathewe of the woman that had an issew of blood &amp; of the rulers daughter, newly translated oute of hyghe Almayne.</title>
                  <title>Epistel aus dem Propheten Jeremia. English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541. Sermon upon the ix. chapter of Mathewe.</author>
                  <author>Lynne, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by S. Mierdman] for Gwalter Lynne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.xlviij. [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "An homily or sermon of the famous doctour Urbanus Rhegius of fayth and resurrection, upon the Gospell of Mathew, in the ix. chapter, of the woman, whiche was grieued with the issew of bloudde, and of the doughter of the chief ruler, which being dead Christ restored to lyfe, preached to the people of Hannouer in Sarou", with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the kyngdome of Christ and the christen liberte.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by Walter Lynne, of Eine Epistel aus dem Propheten Jeremia.</note>
                  <note>Signatures continuous.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through and some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XXXIII, 5-8 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kingdom of God --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:1"/>
            <p>A frutefull and godly Expoſition and declaracion of the kyngdom of Chriſt, and of the chriſten lybertye, made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wordes of the Prophete Ieremye in the xxiij. Chapter, with an expoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the viij. Pſalme, intreatyng of theſame matter, by the famous clerke Doctor Martyn Luther, whereunto is annexed a Godly ſermon, of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Vrbanus Regius, vpon the ix. Chapyter of Mathewe of the woman that had an iſſew of blood &amp; of the rulers daughter, newly tranſlated oute of hyghe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted for Gwalter Lynne. Anno. M.D.xiviij.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt gratiouſe &amp; vertuouſe Lady Elizabeth ſyſter to the Kynges mooſt Royal Maieſtie: Her moſt faythfull dayly Oratour Gwalter Lynne, wyſſheth long lyfe to GODS pleaſure, encreaſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and the lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſiderynge thys tyme (moſte vertuouſe Ladye) to be the tyme of Chriſtes raygne &amp; kyngedome, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein the Goſpel is the rule of the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>xely powers, and mercy is more eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then ſacrifyce: I thoughte that I coulde not gratify your grace more with any kynde of obſequye, that I coulde ſhewe through the ſlender ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes, that it hathe pleaſed the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to endue me withall, then yf
<pb facs="tcp:4167:3"/>I ſhoulde ſet forth in the Englyſh to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſome godly leſſon of ſome learned and Chriſtian teacher, concernyng theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, I haue therfore tranſlated into the Engliſhe long this little boke of mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Martine Luthers doyng, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the kyngedome of Chriſte and Chriſtian libertie, made vpon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of Ieremye the Prophete. And becauſe I know that a good thing can not be to often nor to muche ſpoken of. I haue added hereunto another piece of theſame mans labours, a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that he made vpon the eyghte Pſalme. Lorde, our Lorde, &amp;c. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the ſame matter, and couſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng that fayth in the bloude of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte our ſufficient price and raunſome, &amp; the hope of the reſurrection theſe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal bodyes, is moſt neceſſary to be kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen to al chriſtians. I haue alſo added in the ende of this litle boke, a ſermon made by the famouſe doctour Vrba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Regius, concernyng theſame, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ix. Chapyter of Mathewe, occaſyon taken by the mencyon of the woman, that ſuffered the bloude flixe
<pb facs="tcp:4167:3"/>and the rulers daughter.</p>
            <p>Howe pithilye, learnedly and chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anlye the, theſe matters be handled, it ſhal not nede me to reporte, knowing that your grace delyteth more in the, the pervſyng &amp; readynge of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours themſelues, then of any enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mion or prayſe, that can be geuen vnto them, willynge all other therfore to followe your graces example herein. I committe this my labour vnto your grace, as a moſt ſure toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my good wyll to gratifie your grace by ſetting forth and furthering to my power, the trueth of Chriſt, who alway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es preſerue your gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to muche ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and lyfe wythout ende. So be it.</p>
            <p>Your graces faythfull and dayly Oratour Gwalter Lynne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:4"/>
            <head>Of the kyngdom of Chriſt</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ieremye in the xxiij. Chap.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholde the tyme co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth ſaith the Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wil rayſe vp vnto Dauid a righ teous brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che, &amp; he ſhal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpere with wyſedome, &amp; ſhal ſet vp equitie and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes agayne in earth.</p>
                  <p>In his tyme ſhal Iuda be ſaued, and Iſrael ſhaldwell without feare: &amp; this is the name, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall call hym, the Lord our righteouſnes.</p>
                  <p>And therfore beholde, the tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth (ſaith the Lord) that it ſhal be no more ſayd, the Lord lyueth, which brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> land of Egipte. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord
<pb facs="tcp:4167:4"/>and the Chriſten liberte. lyueth, which brought forth &amp; led the ſeed of the houſe of Iſrael, out of the Northlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and from all countries, where I haue ſcattred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and they ſhaldwel in theyr owne lande agayne.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Epiſtle, or prophecye of Ieremie, is Chriſt ſhewed vnto vs, what he is, and what his kyngedome is, howe he ſhal rule, and howe they that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hys kyngedom ſhal dwel without feare. Firſt ſayth the Prophete, that Chriſt is the braunche and ſeed of Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid, Euen ſo ſayth alſo Saynct Paull to the Rumayns in the .i. That God hath cauſed hys Goſpel of hys. ſonne to be prophecyed by the Prophetes in the ſcriptures, that he ſhould be ſuche a Lorde, whiche ſhould be borne of the ſeed of Dauid (as pertaynyng to the fleſſhe) and yet myghtelye decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:4167:5"/>to be the ſonne of God after the ſpirite that ſanctifyeth &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> Euen ſuche a ſayeng is this alſo, and therfore it is cuydent that the hole olde Teſtament ſerueth vnto thys purpoſe, that we may ſee, that all thynges, whiche we nowe preache and beleue are perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, euen as they were ſhewed &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyed before, as we ſhall further marke and perceyue in the proceſſe.</p>
            <p>Ye haue heard that it was ſaid vnto Abraham,
<note place="margin">Ge. xxij</note> Gen. xxij. In thy ſeed ſhall al the nations of the earth be bleſſed. Thys is a Goſpel, wherewith the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers were ſuſteyned a very long tyme, but it was not yet fulfilled, for he ſayth: It ſhal come to paſſe, that all nacyons ſhalbe bleſſed. In thys ſayng is it ſurely promyſed vnto Abraham, that this ſeed ſhoulde be borne of hys generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that he ſhould not nede to grope here &amp; there, as in the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of Adam, wheras they had alſo a Goſpel, but it was very dark, namely where as God ſayde vnto the ſerpent, Gene.
<note place="margin">Gen. iij.</note> iij. I wyl put enemitye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the, and the woman, and
<pb facs="tcp:4167:5"/>betwene thi ſeed and her ſeed, the ſame ſhal treade doune thy heade, and thou ſhalt treade vpon his hele. Whiche is ſpoken altogether of Chriſte, that he ſhould treade doune the deuills heade and all nacions ſhoulde be bleſſed in hym.</p>
            <p>In all theſe ſaynges it appeareth clearly, that Chriſte muſt be God and man, that he muſt dye and ryſe agayne and receyue an euerlaſting kyngdome here vpon earth, whiche onely is done by his worde. All whiche thinges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be not expreſſely mencio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe wordes, yet they are neuer theles contayned there in vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and it may well be gathered of the wordes, yf the Texte be indifferently loked vpon, and merked. But yf a man do paſſe euer the wordes vnaduiſedly and vndiſcretely, without any further conſideracion, than can no ſuch thing appeare to be in them. As in this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yenge. In thy ſeed ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſſed. They be fewe and ſhorte wordes, but yf thou marke them dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, thou ſhalt fyud therein,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:6"/>that Chriſte is God and man and that he muſt dye and ryſe agayne from the deade. For yf he ſhall bleſſe (whiche is as muche as to take awaye the curſe) then truely muſt he be aboue the curſe which curſe is nothing elles, but death ſynne, and all myſchiefe, yf he ſhall do this, then muſte he nedes haue power to take awaye ſynne &amp; death, &amp; to geue lyfe, where vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it muſt nedes followe that he is more then a pure man. For noman is able to do ſuche workes but God alone, and he that doth this worke, muſt nedes be God alſo. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, yf he ſhall be the naturall ſeede of Abraham, then muſte he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be man alſo. Nowe yf he be a man, then muſte he nedes be mortall, or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he coulde not be called Abrahams ſonne. Agayne, yf he ſhall brynge the bleſſinge vppon all nations of the earthe, then muſte he nedes lyue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, and for euer, where vppon it foloweth, that he is mortall, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo ſhalt thou fynde it in all other places of the ſcripture, yf the
<pb facs="tcp:4167:6"/>ſaynges be iuſtely and diligently mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked. But we will ſee from worde to worde, what Ieremie doth notifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in this ſayeng, that we may fynd this alſo in lyke maner. Fyrſt ſayth he thus.</p>
            <q>Beholde, the tyme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſayeth the Lorde, that I will rayſe vp vnto Dauid a righteous braunche.</q>
            <p>Theſe wordes are vndoubteb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken of Chriſte, wherein is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, as the Prophecye declareth, that he ſhoulde come of the ſynage and ſtocke of Dauid. Therefore ſaith Sayncte Paule well,
<note place="margin">Rom. i</note> that after the fleſſhe he is borne of the ſeed of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. For the Prophete Ieremie would deſcribe the ſauiour plenteoufly, that he myght be perfytely knowen, what he ſhoulde be, and from whence he ſhoulde come, becauſe of them, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4167:7"/>cyther at that tyme or afterwarde ſhould come vnto the fayth &amp; beleue in him that they ſhould not nede to grope after him here or there, or ſeke him any where elles. Therfore doth he knyite hym vnto the generation and ſtock of Dauid, from whence men ſhould loke for hym vndoubtedly. With ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue the Prophetes conforted the people, and warned them that they ſhoulde marke diligently vpon this ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neration, and that they ſhoulde be throughly perſwaded, that he ſhould come none other waye, but from the ſtocke of Dauid.</p>
            <p>This knewe the Iewes well ynough out of the ſayenges of the ſcripture, &amp; were as ſure of it, as we knowe &amp; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be leue, that Chriſt ſhal come agayn at the later daye. Therefore ſayd alſo the Angel Gabriell vnto Marie.
<note place="margin">Luce. i.</note> Luc. i. The Lord God ſhall geue vnto hym, the ſeate of his father Dauid, and he ſhall raigne ouer the houſe of Iacob for euer, and of his kyndgdome ſhalbe none ende.</p>
            <p>He ſayeth: I wyll rayſe vp, that is
<pb facs="tcp:4167:7"/>to ſay: I will ſette &amp; ſtablyſſhe it, that it may ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſure. As though he would ſaye: The people of the Iewes haue bene hitherto afflicted and troubled with their kynges. For where as I haue ſometyme ſtyred vp vnto them,
<note place="margin">iiij. Re. xviij.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne good kynge (as Ezechiam) they haue had tenne bad for hym. But I wil once rayſe vp, and ordeyne a kynge, which ſhall continue. For euer but I will not rayſe hym for this cauſe, that he ſhall aſſaulte any man. But he hym ſelfe ſhall be aſſaulted of the world, of the deuill, &amp; of all whatſoeuer is great and mightie in the worlde, but I will ſo ſett hym, that he ſhall ſtand faſt and ſure, and his enemies ſhall not preuaile agaynſt hym.</p>
            <p>And he ſayeth: he will rayſe vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Dauid, a righteous braunche. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſaith Sachary alſo,
<note place="margin">Sach. ix</note> that he is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and a ſauiour. Lo ſaith he: Thy kynge cometh vnto the a righteous kyng and alſo a ſauiour. On this wyſe dyd the Prophetes ſee Chriſt (euen as we ſee hym alſo) namely, a kinge that iuſtifieth the worlde. For the worlde is
<pb facs="tcp:4167:8"/>nothinge elles, but a ſtable full of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftes. The worlde is the kyngdome of the deiull, and bloude and fleſſhe is her houſſeholde, of whoſe vngracious and wycked aſſanltes, al ſaynctes haue euer complayned, and muſte alſo euer more complayne, as Paule declareth to the Romaynes in the vij.
<note place="margin">Ro. vij.</note> Therefore did the holy Fathers and Prophetes, without ceaſſing deſyre, and crye after this righteous brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, after this Chriſt whiche ſhoulde make them iuſte and righteous, and take awaye ſynne and death. And this alſo doo all good and faithfull hertes (yea the vnfaythefull alſo) ſtyll contynually deſyre. For who would not rather haue lyfe then death and rather haue righteouſnes then ſynne?
<note place="margin">Ro. vij.</note> Therefore cryeth Paule. O wretched man that I am, who ſhall delyuer me from this body of deathe? But thus crye not all men, for they fele it not all: The deuill poſſeſſeth the heries of many, and ſeduceth them that they can not thynke therevpon.</p>
            <p>Thus may we ſee that this is the Summe, or Chiefe poynt of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:8"/>that this kynge is iuſte and righteous, that is, withoute all ſynne, where by he is ſegregated, and ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from all other men, whiche all are vnrighteous, wicked and ſynners. Nowe yf he be righteous, than maye he not be borne after the maner as other mennes Children be borne. Therefore it foloweth that his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſte be a virgyn. For it is ſayde of all other men, by the Prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. Pſalm. li. Beholde,
<note place="margin">Pſal. li.</note> I was ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in wickednes, and in ſynne hath my mother conceyued me. Therefore muſte this kynge nedes haue had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maiſter, that he was conceyned and borne withoute ſynne. For yf he ſhall be righteous, and not gyltie of deathe, then maye he not, be borne of a woman, by the helpe of a man (as we are). But he muſt be pure from his byrthe.</p>
            <p>But howe cometh this to paſſe, that he is pure, and not ſubiecte vnto death? From whence cometh this vnto hym? He ſhoulde come from the ſtocke of Dauid, And is not the kynred
<pb facs="tcp:4167:9"/>of Dauid alſo vnder the malediction? Yes truely, but here vnto muſt a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin be vſed out of the ſtocke of Dauid the other hath the holy Ghooſt execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he hath purified this byrth, as the Angell ſayde vnto the virgyne Mary Luc. i.
<note place="margin">Luce. i.</note> The holy Ghooſt ſhall come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, and the power of the hygeſte ſhall ouerſhadowe the. Therfore alſo that holy thinge whiche ſhalbe borne, ſhalbe called the ſonne of God. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue we ſuche a kyng, which hath a name before all other kynges, that he is righteous, and righteous in all thinges. In ſo muche that he alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth other good and righteous. And ſo will theſe wordes that he muſte nedes be God and man, and be borne of a vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyn, albeit that theſe wordes do not clearly and manifeſtely expreſſe it, yet bringe they ſo much with them, yf they be throughly ſearched.</p>
            <p>But where he calleth hym a braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, that is ſpoken after the maner of the Ebrewes, whiche calle the children braunches, whiche waxe and growe eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the herbes, buſſhes &amp; trees do grow
<pb facs="tcp:4167:9"/>which ſoundeth not ſo well in oure ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as in the eares of the Iewes. So ſayth God alſo in Eſa. Cap. xiiij.
<note place="margin">Eſa xiiij</note> of the kyngdome of Babylon. I will roote oute the name &amp; remnaunte, ſonne and ſonnes ſonne of Babilon. For the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the parentes, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the braunches &amp; boughes come oute of the trees. Therfore ſaith alſo Eſaye in the xi. Chap.
<note place="margin">Eſa. xi.</note> A rod ſhall come forth oute of the ſtocke of Ieſſe oute of a ſtocke, whiche nowe is deade (ſayth he) ſhall growe a braunche, that is oute of an olde withered ſtocke. Where of noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loked for any thinge to ſpringe forth of it. For Dauid was dead, &amp; his kynred laye altogether vnder fote, euen in the aſſhes. Pilate was at Ieruſalem in the ſtede of the kyngdome of Dauid, &amp; the Romayns had the rule and dominion, ſo that of the kynred and ſtocke of Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid was very littel remembraunce, and lay hydde ſkant in two or thre per ſonnes, as in Ioſeph and Mary, which were at Nazareth.</p>
            <p>Now ſayth God, let the ſtock waxe olde and hole withered, I am able to
<pb facs="tcp:4167:10"/>reuine hym, when ye loke leaſte of all for his commynge, then ſhall he come, whan men thinke, that the ſtocke of Dauid is cleane extincte, and decayed and paſte recoueringe, then will I come and make hym to floryſſhe, and to ſpringe furth, and to bringe furth fruite. There maye ye ſe howe the Prophetes agree together, and go all vpon Dauid, that oute of his ſtocke and kynrede ſhoulde come the iuſte and righteous kynge, whiche ſhoulde delyuer his from ſynne, death, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, hell, and from all euyll, and make them ſafe for euer. Whereof Ieremie nowe ſpeaketh further, and ſayeth.</p>
            <q>And he ſhall reigne a kynge, and ſhall proſpere with wyſedome, and ſhall ſet vp equitie and righteouſnes agayne in earth.</q>
            <p>Theſe wordes ſounde, as though he
<pb facs="tcp:4167:10"/>woulde ſignifye, that there is no righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in earthe. I meane not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the righteouſnes, whiche is of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure before God, but alſo of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde righteouſnes of the worlde, whiche is but a very beggers cloake. For the worlde is a right ſchoole of the deuills vnthriftes. Therefore hath God alſo ordeyned the ſwearde, and alſo the hangeman, that yet a lyttel parte of righteouſnes mighte be in earthe. For with the righteouſnes whiche is of valoure before God, it will not be. In earth is nothinge but vnrightuoſnes, bothe in the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Gouernaunce, and alſo in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall. Gouernaunce is nothinge but blaſpheminge of God. For thus ſayth the Pſalme. xiiij.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. xiiij. and liij. Rom. iij</note> The Lorde loked donne from heauen vpon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men to ſee, yf there were any that woulde vnderſtande and ſeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God. But they were all gone oute of the waye, and were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become abhominable, there is none that doeth good, no not one. &amp; cete. There geueth he a ſhorte
<pb facs="tcp:4167:11"/>ſentence, ſayenge that there is not one good. God to then, this is ſure, yf a man will beholde the worlde euen from heauen dounewarde, he ſhall ſe nothinge but mere blyndenes iniquitie, vnrighteouſnes, and fooli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhenes, and nothinge elles, but a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble full of vngrations vnthriftes, and not muche better then ſhe was in the tyme of Noah. When God through the floudde, cauſed all men to peryſhe ſauinge eyght perſons.</p>
            <p>Howe be it, very fewe do felt ſuche blyndenes and vnrighteouſnes, but onely ſuche as by the lawe are taught and inſtructed, as in thoſe da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes the holy Fathers and Prophetes, the common people wandereth euen as the cattell.</p>
            <p>Nowe this Thild, whiche ſhoulde be borne of Dauid, righteous and iuſte, withoute ſynne ſhall be the kyng whiche ſhall ſtande,
<note place="margin">Eſaye xi. b. Rom. xix. b.</note> and rule for euer. Nowe for as muche then as he is a braunche and a twygge of the ſtocke of Dauid. He muſte nedes be mortall
<pb facs="tcp:4167:11"/>for bodely is he borne in this tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lyfe, and therefore muſte he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des dye. But ſeyuge he ſhall ſtande allwaye and rule for euer, then muſte he alſo be immortall. Howe will this frame? Euen thus he muſte ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayue from the deade. This is it that Sayncte Peter meaneth. Where as in the Actes of the Apoſtles, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth onte of the Prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, that it was impoſſible, that he ſhoulde be holden of deathe. Acto. ij.
<note place="margin">Act. ij. Pſalm. xvi.</note> Pſalme. xvi. Vvhat was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon? For he ſhall continue a kynge, and rule for euer. And ſo ſieſte thou in theſe wordes euery where notifyed the reſurrection of Chriſte. That he muſte be borne and dye, and yet rule alwayes, therfore muſt hene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ryſe agayne from death.</p>
            <p>Further more (ſayeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete) that this kynge ſhall proſpere with wiſedome, that is, he ſhall rule with vnderſtandinge and diſcretion, as it is written, of Dauid. i. Reg.
<note place="margin">i. Reg. xviij.</note> xviij. He behaued hym ſelfe wyſely in all his wayes, that is, he was the
<pb facs="tcp:4167:12"/>mooſte circumſpecte, and mooſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous amonge all them that were in the courte of Saule. Euen ſo ſayethe here Ieremie alſo of this kynge, that he ſhall proſpere with wyſedome, that is, he ſhall behaue hym ſelfe wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely. Hitherto haue we hearde of the perſone of this kynge, namely that he ſhoulde come from the ſtocke of Dauid, that he ſhoulde be a man, and be borne of a virgyne, and ſhoulde be a righteous kynge, whiche is all to be vnderſtande of his perſone.</p>
            <p>Nowe foloweth it further, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer this kynge hath, he ſhall not kepe for hym ſelfe, but ſhall beſtowe it and geue it vnto menne, and this meaneth the Prophete where he ſayth: He ſhall proſpere with wyſedome, that is, he ſhall rule with no nother thinge, but onely wyth wyſedome. As though he woulde ſaye, he ſhall not occupye harnas, ſweardes, gounes, bowes and ſpeares, but he ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to make men righteous, after a newe and a ſtraunge guyſe, not with rakynge or hangynge, but with, or by
<pb facs="tcp:4167:12"/>the Goſpell, he ſhall take the people whereby they may beſt be taken. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, by the herte, and not by the neck to thintent that they may ſubdue them ſelues, and be willinge to folowe him. There ſeeſt thou that he is a kynge, for this cauſe, that he helpeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and doth the ſame withoute ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the ſwearde, onely by his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. For the whiche cauſe he is alſo ryſen from the deade, and cauſeth his Goſpell to be preached, through the holy Ghooſt, throughoute all the worlde.</p>
            <p>After this ſayethe the Prophete, that this kynge ſhall ſet vp equitie and righteouſnes in earthe. Theſe two wordes Equitie and righteouſnes doeſte thou reade very often together in the Scripture, as in Eſaye,
<note place="margin">Eſa. ix.</note> in the ix. he ſhall ſitte vpon the ſeate of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, and in his kyngedome, to ſette vp the ſame, and to ſtablyſſhe it with equitie and righteouſnes, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, for euermore, where alſo he ſpeaketh of the kynge dome of Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:4167:13"/>and it is as muche in oure ſpech as to iudge righteouſly whiche the Iewes doo pronounce with two wordes, and yet they meane no more than that we call righteouſnes. Howe be it, there by are ſignifyeth theſe two poyntes to leaue that whiche is euill, and to do that whiche is good, for theſe are the two poyntes whiche belonge to the righteouſnes. And for as muche as there are no more, but euen theſe two poyntes, therefore vſeth the ſcripture theſe two wordes, Iudicium, and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia. Through Iuſtice or equitie, doth God punyſſhe, that is, he putteth awaye that whiche is euill. Through the righteouſnes maketh he the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be good and righteous, and preſerueth, and defendeth innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. Nowe this kynge is not onely for hym ſelfe iuſte and righteous, but he fulfilleth that, whiche the worlde, with her righteouſnes and workes is not able to do. Namely, that the people myghte be righteous. Vvho did euer ſe ſuche a Kynge? He ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the ryghte hande of God,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:13"/>hys heauenly father, and yet ſhall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye the people, and thys ſhall alſo be done here vpon earthe, whiche is yet more merneylous? But howe cometh thys to paſſe? Euen thus, The kyngedome of Chriſte is a ſpirituall kyngedome, whiche ruleth herein earth, and yet it is not of the earh, but of heauen. Thys could neuer no King brynge to paſſe, that he had ſet vp a kyngdome, whiche were in earth, and yet were not terreſtrial, but celeſtiall. Wherfore thys worke declareth, that thys Kynge muſt be more then a bare or pure man.</p>
            <p>For he that knoweth thys ſcience, &amp; hathe the power, that he is aboue ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and can iuſtifye ſynne, theſame muſte nedes be God, for God onely iuſtifyeth the vngodly,
<note place="margin">Ro. iiij.</note> as Paul ſayth Roma. in the .iiij. And for as much, as thys Kyng performeth, and bryngeth to paſſe ſuche thynges, it followeth therfore, that he is very God, ſence he hath the honour, and doth the workes, which onely belonge to God, Nowe then, yf he can bryng to paſſe, that the
<pb facs="tcp:4167:14"/>people maye be delyuered from theyr ſynnes, and by that meanes make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryghteous, then can he alſo ſoone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer them from death, for where as is no ſynne, there can be no death, for the ſtynge of death is ſynne, as Paul ſaith to the Torinthians.
<note place="margin">i. Co. xv</note> i. Cor. xv. for yf there were no ſynne, then ſhoulde death haue no myghte nor power, and thus doth thys Kynge delyuer vs from ſynne, and death, from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, from hell, and from all infelicite, and geueth vs the eternall ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and euerlaſtynge lyfe. He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth GOD oure father, and geueth vs the kyngedome of heauen, Nowe, thys is no man able to do, neyther angell, nor ſaynete, neither alſo Mary the mother of God, but onely GOD hym ſelf, whereout it followeth then, that thys kyng muſte nedes be God, and although it be not expreſſed with manifeſt wordes, yet do the wordes and the vnderſtandynge of thys ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge, brynge it with them, that he is verye GOD and man, So good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye coulde the Prophetes ſpeake of
<pb facs="tcp:4167:14"/>Chriſte, and counterfayte hym ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentely vnto vs, that it is to be mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neyled, to thintent, that we ſhould not myſſe hym. Here ryſeth nowe a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyon, Thou ſaydeſt euen nowe, howe that all ſaynctes muſte crye with Sayncte Paule, ouer ſynne, &amp; death. O wretched man, that I am, who ſhall delyuer me from thys body ſubdued vnto death. Here ſe we alſo, that the Chriſtians dye, yea the better Chriſtians, the heauyer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath they ſuffre? what meaneth thys? call ye that delyueryng from death &amp; ſynne? Thys is it, that I haue ſayde. It is a ſpiritual kyngedome, and kyuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of faythe, It wyll ſtande in faythe, and men muſte alſo beholde it with the eyes of fayth, Otherwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe can no man at no tyme vnderſtande it, for there remayneth yet, that death muſte deuoure vs, The Emperours and Cyrannous haue behedded the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and holye martyrs, Sayncte Paule was fayne to ſtretche for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the hys heade, Moreouer there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
<pb facs="tcp:4167:15"/>yet the luſtes and inclinations towarde ſynne, There be alſo manye hereſyes and ſectes, whiche al obiecte themſelues agayuſte the Chriſtians, where is here lyfe? where is here the ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of death, which is prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched in thys kyngedome?</p>
            <p>Vnto that do I anſwer thus: We haue dominion and rule, ouer ſyune &amp; ouer death, howe be it, we haue not yet ouercome them, and we be not yet delyuered from them, for the text ſaith that the Kynge is yet workynge, For he doth alwayes rayſe vp righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and maketh yet ſtyliuſte &amp; rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, lyke as a Tayllour which maketh a garment, as longe as he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thereouer, ſo longe is he in the worke, and it can not be ſayd, that the garment be al hole fynyſhed. Euen ſo is the kyngdome of Chriſte in earthe ſtyll in worke, he worketh and rayſeth dayly thereouer, and ſhal ſo continue vntyl the latter daye, And then ſhal al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynges fyrſt be made ryght perfecte. In the meane ſeaſon do the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtyl fall in ſyune, albeit agayuſt theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4167:15"/>wyl. But thys aduauntage hath a Chriſtian, although he do fele the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, yet is he neuertheles lorde ouer it, but to that ende can he not brynge it, that he myghte cleane be delyuered from ſynne, vntyl the olde wretche dye cleane, and peryſhe.</p>
            <p>Therfore albeit that the Chriſtians fall, yet is Chriſte preſent with them, which ruleth by hys ſpirite, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſynne, and ſtyll rayſeth them vp agayne, ſayeng, aryſe brother, be of good comfort, there is no daunger. And ſo is Chriſt alwayes in the battel and in workynge, and fyghteth with oure enemyes. They do often reſiſte agaynſt hym, but at the laſte he obtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the victory, and they are depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Euen ſo goeth it alſo with them, that are hys, in whome God trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and ouercometh thorough Chriſt. Therfore ſayth Paule. i. Cor. xv.
<note place="margin">i. Co. xv</note> But thankes be vnto God, which hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs victory, thorough oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. And. ij. Cor. ij. ſaith he.
<note place="margin">ij. Cor. ij</note> Thankes be vnto God, which alway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es geueth vs the victory in Chriſt. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:4167:16"/>ſometyme one be put to the worſte, yet is Chriſt at hande, and lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hym vp agayne, ſayenges vp bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, aryſe, thou haſt no hurte, at it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne ſtyll, thou muſt nedes fighte it oute, it can not be done withoute fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, but take hede that thou lye not ſtyl. There is euermore fallynge and ryſynge agayne, as long as we lyue in thys worlde.</p>
            <p>Nowe,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> as Chriſte hath ouercome ſynne, euen ſo doth he alſo ouercome death, when death is at hande, &amp; preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vpon the, and wyll deſtroye the, then is Chriſt preſent with the, and ſayth, at it luſtely, he can not hurte the and although he do ſtryke the, it ſhall be no more vnto the, then yf thou we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to ſlepe, Nowe go to, it is but a ſmal matter, within this ſhorte houre it ſhal be better A man may fele, that death is bitter and ſharpe, But he can not prenayle nor triumphe ouer the. For Chriſte hath made hym faynte, hys ſtynge or darte is made to blunt, He hathe weryed hym ſelfe vpon CHRISE, whiche hath ouercome
<pb facs="tcp:4167:16"/>hym, and treaden hym vnder hys fete.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo goeth it alſo with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes and Hereſyes, and with all other aduerſities, whiche all can not hurte vs, for we haue one in heauen, vnto whome all thynges are poſſyble, and be is able to preſerue vs, that nothing ſhall happen vnto vs withoute hys wyll.</p>
            <p>Therfore I ſaye, that the outward temptatious, maye well remayne, but yet oure fayth can not be hurte, for there remayneth yet in the herte a certayne power agaynſte ſynne, and a courage agaynſte death, and all aduerſities. Thys is it, that CHRISTE continueth in hys offyce, and dryueth hys worke, ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth with ſynne, and fyghteth with death, vntyll hys kyngedome be at complyſſhed, that is, vntill the latter daye.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we heard nowe, howe the Prophete Ierempe hath declared Chriſte, what hys perſon is, and what hys offyce ſhall be, namely,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:17"/>that hys offyce tendeth to thys ende, that he proſpere with wyſedome, and rule wyſely, ſo that he rayſe equitie &amp; ryghteouſnes in earth. And thys offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce or dominion, is comprehended in theſe wordes, whereby it doth clearly appeare, that his kyngedom is not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble, and bodely, but that it muſte be an inviſyble and ſpiritual kyngdome, although it be here in earthe, that is, among men, which lyue here in earth. Vvherfore it followeth, that it is a kyngedom of fayth, and can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended with bodely eyes, Thereof haue ye heard now ſufficiently, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it followeth further in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete.</p>
            <q>In hys tyme ſhall Iuda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be ſaued, and Iſraell ſhall dwell without feare.</q>
            <p>That is, at the ſame tyme of the braunche of Dauid, when thys Kyng ſhall rule, then ſhal Iuda be ſaued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, at that tyme wyl I helpe the,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:17"/>and delyuer the oute of all thy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo that thys is a helpyng or dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryng from all aduerſities, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all daungers.</p>
            <p>Theſe two ſayenges do alſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye vnto vs, that thys kyngdome, is not a bodely kyngdome, for ye knowe that the kyngdome of the Iewes was diuided into two kyngedoms, Into the kyngedome of Iuda, and into the kyngedome of Iſrael. The tenne try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes had one Kyng of theyr owne, and were called the kyngedom of Iſraell. Afterwarde began the kyngedom of Iuda and Ben Iamin, and that was called the kyngedom of Iuda. For the people were diuided, and eyther of them had hys, propre Kynge, Nowe the great kyngedome dyd God reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte, bycauſe of theyr ſynnes and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and ſo diſperſed and deſtroyed it, that he neuer rayſed it vp agayne, but ſcattered it amonge the Heathen, amonge the Medes, and Aſſyrianes. Vvherfore he neuer ſent them anye Prophetes, neyther dyd he ſterevp any amonge them, And ſo dyd thys
<pb facs="tcp:4167:18"/>be ſeparated the one from the other, and ſhall neuer come together agayn, ſo that it myght be made agayne one kyngedome, howe ſayth then here the Prophete, Iuda ſhalbe ſaued, and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſhal dwel withoute feare, and ſo coupleth Iuda, and Iſrael together, &amp; the texte ſoundeth as though it ſhould be one kyngedome and one peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Thys maye not be vnderſtande bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely, that Iuda and Iſrael both ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de come agayne bodely into the land together, but it is done vnder Chriſt, ſpiritually in the faythe, whan he is publyſſhed throughe the holye Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, For when Chriſt was preached at Ieruſalem, there were many Iewes conuerted, and beleued in Chriſt, both of the ſtocke of Iuda, and alſo of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, for vpon Vvhyteſonday there were at Ieruſalem, of Aſſiriens, Cili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Medes, and of al nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnder heauen three thouſande co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in one day, &amp; cleaued vnto the ſeede of Dauid, namely vnto Chriſt. Therfore maye not thys texte be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande
<pb facs="tcp:4167:18"/>of the bodely kyngedome, but of the ſpiritual kyngdom of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, for that Iuda and Iſraell ſhoulde come together agayne, and be made one kyngdom, could neuer be brought to paſſe, vnder no bodely Kynge. Therfore whan the Prophetes ioyne theſe two nations together, namelye Iuda and Iſrael, then wyll they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſignifye Chriſtes kyngedome. And ſo here alſo ſayth the Prophete Ieremye, that Iuda ſhall be ſaued, and Iſrahel ſhal dwell without feare whiche was done vnder Chriſte, for otherwyſe came they neuer together, neyther ſhal they at anye tyme here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after come together agayne.</p>
            <p>Wherfore ſayth he then,
<note place="margin">Nota.</note> Iuda ſhal be ſaued, and Iſraell ſhall dwel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute feare? Therfore, as thoughe he woulde ſaye, as longe as theſe kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſtande, they ſhall be aſſaulted, and at the laſte ſhal they be deſtroyed alſo the kyngly generation ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken awaye, Howe be it they ſhall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue helpe. It is nowe greuous vnto Iuda, they are caryed awaye into a
<pb facs="tcp:4167:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:20"/>ſtraunge lande, where as they muſte ſubmitte them ſelues and ſerue other, Notwithſtandynge I wyll ones rayſe vp an helpe, that my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall alwayes haue the vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande, althoughe the hole worlde ſhoulde be madde and rage for it. But thys vnderſtode not the Iewes. Beſydes thys, here is ſignifyed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that Chriſtes kyngedome is ſubdued vnto the holy Croſſe, for this can neuer fayll, whereſoeuer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes kyngedome is preached through the holye Goſpell, there foloweth by and by the croſſe,
<note place="margin">Luc. xi.</note> and perſecution ſurely, Thys ſignifyeth the Parable in Luke. Cap. xi. where the Lorde Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte ſpeaketh on thys wyſe, when a ſtronge man armed, watcheth hys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>houſe, that whiche he poſſeſſeth is in peace, But when a ſtronger then he cometh vpon him, &amp; ouercometh him, he taketh from hym hys harnas, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein he truſted, &amp; diuideth his goodes.</p>
            <p>Howe goeth that to worke?
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> Euen thus, when the holye Goſpell goeth not abroade, then is the deuyl in the
<pb facs="tcp:4167:20"/>worlde, and ruleth mightelye, with good peace and reſte, and all men go euen ſtepynge into hell, as we haue ſene hitherto, vnder the Papacye, there was an outwarde peace, but it was not an vpryght peace. But in the holye Goſpell is the true peace preached, vnder the whiche is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned mere diſcorde, becauſe of the Tyrauntes and Sectes. Therfore becauſe that nowe the holye Goſpel ryſeth, whiche beginneth to laye hand vpon the deuyls kyngedome, and to declare, what maner of felowe the deuyl is, howe blacke he is, and that hys kyngedom, howe holy and good ſoeuer it appeare, leadeth vnto dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. All the worlde is ſet agaynſte it, whatſoeuer is great and holy, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth thereon, and it greueth the deuill that his kyngdom is deſtroyed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeth he ſtirre vp all whatſoeuer he is able to make, &amp; to bringe vp, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge: I ſlepe and ſitte in good peace and tranquillite for a greate ſeaſon, but ye wyll diſtourbe my oute of my ſlepe abyde, and I wyll breake you
<pb facs="tcp:4167:21"/>of your ſlepe agayne, and I wyl cauſe you to haue trouble ynough, yf ye ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue delyte, in trouble and tribulation, ye ſhall haue ynough of it. This doth he alſo very largely, as we ſee, for as ſoone as we receyue the Goſpell, we haue peace, and alſo no peace, It prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth peace, &amp; yet followeth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt trouble.</p>
            <p>Howe whereas Chriſte ruleth through hys Goſpell and worde, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſhalbe helpe and ſuccour, thys cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he to be preached and declared vnto vs, The deuyll maye well rayſe vp Tyrauntes and Sectes, and cauſe the hole worlde to rebell agaynſte the Goſpell, let them rage and be madde, they ſhal not preuayle agayuſt it, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof be thou ſure, for of theſe ſaye n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and promyſes is the ſcripture full,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. xxxiij.</note> as where the .xxxiij. Pſalm ſayth. The Lorde bryngeth the Counſayll of the Heathen to nought, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the deuyſes of the people of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne effecte.
<note place="margin">Pſal. ij.</note> And in the ſeconde Pſalme ſayth Dauid, that the Heathen rage furiouſly, and the people Imagine
<pb facs="tcp:4167:21"/>the kynges of the earth ſtande vp, and the rulers take counſayll together, agaynſte the Lorde and his anoynted. But he addeth a littell worde thereto, whiche is called vaynely, and ſayeth. He that dwelleth in heauen, ſhal laugh them to ſcorne, the Lord ſhal haue them in deriſion. And why? Becauſe he is to ſtronge and to myghtie for them, he is able to bryng their deuyſes to nought yea though there were a thouſande ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſo many of them, they ſhall gette nothinge at his hande, they maye be ſure. But here vnto perteyneth a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fayth, and a ſharp ſight, to knowledge theſe thinges.</p>
            <p>Therfore are theſe earneſte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that the Prophet ſayth: Iuda ſhall be helped, or ſaued,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> and Iſrahel ſhall dwell ſafe, or withoute feare, yf thou doeſt not behold them with faith, thou ſhalt ſurely fynde the contrary parte. For call ye this helpinge, or is this peace, when Chriſt the kyng hym ſelfe is hanged vpon the Croſſe? When the apoſtles heades be ſmiten of. And when the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be put from houſe
<pb facs="tcp:4167:22"/>and lande, and are dryuen from towne to towne? Item, When Chriſte, as he ſayth hym ſelfe in Mathewe.
<note place="margin">Mat. x.</note> Capit. x. ſendeth forth his Apoſtles and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, as ſhepe amonge wolues? vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there ſhoulde be prety peace? Club<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and Halbardes, or dogges ſhould be ſent amonge them? I ſuppoſe alſo that it is called a kyngedome of peace, and of Saluation. It might well ynough be called a kyngedome of warre, where as is nothinge but kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and murtheringe? Yea this is it that I haue ſayde, It is another ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of kyngedome, than menſe with their eyes. It apeareth outwardly, as though it were damned, as though it were forſaken and deſtitute of helpe, but inwardely is it meare peace and ſaluation, there is the battayll ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by faith, In the ſight of the world doth it ſomtyme apeare as, though the Chriſtians laye vnderfote, for they are kylled and murthered euermore lyke the Cattell, and the vngodly ſwymme alofte. The Sectes and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſyes haue the victory and triumphe.
<pb facs="tcp:4167:22"/>But what is it?
<note place="margin">Sap. v.</note> It laſteth not longe than are all thinges tourned, there ſhall the vngodly peryſſhe, and the doctrine of the ſpirites of errour ſhall be forgotten. There ſhall it then appeare, howe Chriſte hath holpen and ſuccoured his people. And howe they haue had dominion ouer ſynne, deathe and the deuyll. Vvhiche nowe appeareth very lyttell or nothinge.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo was it in the tyme of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, than were there ſcant thre Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes in the hole Chriſtianite, that preached righte, then was the hole worlde ſeduced with this hereſy, and alſo the Emperour hym ſelfe. Then was there a great perſecution of the Chriſtians, becauſe of this hereſy, in ſo muche that many of them euerywher were banyſſhed; and dryuen oute of the townes and countries, ſo ſore that we reade of no greater perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, then that, whiche was at the tyme of Arrius. Then did it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, as though Chriſte had layen vnderfoote, and Arrius aboue, then
<pb facs="tcp:4167:23"/>thought men, now is it at an ende with Chriſte and with his Chriſtians, the Goſpell is gone, and it is oute nowe. Oute quod he, nay nay: For Chriſte remayned ſtill and the faithe. Where are now thoſe heretykes? Arrius with the Emperour peryſhed, in ſo muche that their names ſtynke more nowe before the worlde, than their doctriue as then was in eſtimation, and beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that, they are all goue to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. But Chriſte is yet a lyue, and his Kyngedome ſtandeth alſo yet ſure.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo at this tyme,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> when men ſaye: There are many Sectes, there are many hereſyes agaynſte the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and it is to be feared that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhalbe put doune, I praye the let them go, they can not leape ouer this ſayenge. Iuda ſhalbe ſaued, &amp; Iſrahel ſhall dwell withoute feare. This fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yenge muſte be true, though the deuill ſaye nay to it, Satan and the worlde will hynder it, and take awaye fayth, but he ſayth, I will ſuffer them to fall, but yet will I help them, and they ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:4167:23"/>dwell ſafe, in deſpite of all them that will lett me. Although there apeare no certeinte (for what certaynte can there be vnder the Croſſe) &amp; the world ſeke the lyfe neuer ſo nygh, &amp; though Satan will take awaye their faith, yet ſhall they dwell withoute feare. And this happeneth alſo vndoubtedly, for where as the Goſpell is, there is ſuche a ſure wall, which is fyrye and of yron and thicker then heauen and earthe. And a thouſande Emperours are not able to ouerthro we this wall a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man. For the worde of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euer.
<note place="margin">Eſa. xl.</note> Wherefore the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians haue mery and quyet conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and the more the world rageth, the bolder they waxe, yea the ſurer this certaynte and boldenes do ſtand. And ſo doth the Tyranne of the world, and the ſectes ſtrengthen the hertes of the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſheweth this texte once agayne, that he ſpeaketh of a ſpiritual kyngdome. For there is no kyngdome ſo myghtie, that euer was able by the ſweard to conquere vnto his ſubiectes
<pb facs="tcp:4167:24"/>ſuche a certaynte and peace. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes haue ben the mooſt mightieſt Lordes, notwitſtandinge they were oftentymes beatten, and coulde neuer bryuge it to that poynte, that they might haue had peace and certayntie, ſomtyme there were foure thouſande ſlayne, and ſomtyme tenne thouſande, to that they had alwayes aſſaultes, and enemitie. It foloweth nowe further in the Prophete.</p>
            <q>And this is the name that they ſhall call hym, euen the Lorde our rightuouſnes.</q>
            <p>The Perſon hath he deſcribed, and alſo the office, and the frute of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, namely, that he ſhall ſette vp equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and righteouſnes, and that the people ſhall haue helpe, and dwell in ſauetie, howe be it vnder the Croſſe and perſecution. Nowe declareth the Prophete, what his name ſhall be, and ſaythe: he ſhall be called, the Lorde oure righteouſnes. The Iewes holde muche of this name in the Ebrewe
<pb facs="tcp:4167:24"/>tonge, whiche we haue tranſlated Lorde, and ſaye: that he may not be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, neyther do they name hym alſo, in ſuche great reuerence do they kepe it, they writtet it vpon no paper, and whan they writte it there on, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the letters, and make ſeant two let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and they alowe it not that the Chriſtians ſhoulde ſe it written. Alſo ſome wicked perſonnes amonge the Iewes, haue deceaued many Princes and Lordes, vnto whome they haue geuen this name in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, and haue tolde them, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer did beare it aboute hym, ſhould not be ſlayne, and that it doth ſerue for more other thinges, of lyke ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. Euen as alſo many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, whiche haue learned it of the Iewes, where wonte to graue this name in golde or ſiluer, and to hange it aboute their neckes, to thintent, that they ſhoulde not be ſhot or woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The cauſe wherfore the Iewes holde ſo muche of this name is this, where as this name Lorde ſtandeth in the
<pb facs="tcp:4167:25"/>ſcripture there doth it ſignifie God in his Godly eſſence and Maieſtie, and there is ſpoken of the very God. The Hebrewe language hath aboute tenne names, whereby ſhe nameth God, amonge the whiche there are many whereby ſhe nameth God, concerning his workes, but this name Iehouah, Lorde, ſignifieth onely God as he is in his Godly eſſence. This difference can we not kepe in oure language, for we do commonly call it Lorde, and can not wreſte nor conſtrayne this worde, that it ſhoulde ſignifie God onely, for we call a Prince Lorde, and a ruler is alſo called Lord, and it is very common to vs in our language. But that we call God alſo a Lorde, this haue we out of the Euangeliſtes, which call him Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, Lorde, whome we do folowe herein leaninge it as we fynde it. The other names in the Ebrewe, are not onely aſſeribed to God, but they are alſo ſpoken to other menne, but this name, Iehouah, is onely attributed to the very lyuinge God.</p>
            <p>For as much nowe as the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:25"/>and the Iewes them ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes that alſo the holy Fathers, and all writters do agree in one, that this name onely &amp; properly appertayneth to the Godly Maieſtie and eſſence, ſo haue we here in the Prophet Ieremie, a mighty ſtronge defence agaynſt the Iewes, and a very excellent great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte for vs Chriſtians. For there is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry mightely grounded this Article, of oure fayth, That Chriſte is a very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall God. I haue my ſelfe reaſoned thereof with the Iewes, euen with the Chiefeſt and beſt learned, whiche knowe the Byble ſo well, that there is neuer a letter in it, but they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode it, and layed this ſayeuge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. But they coulde alledge nothinge agaynſte me, at the laſte, made they this anſwere, and ſayde that they beleued their Talmud, that is, their expoſition, whiche ſpeaketh nothinge of Chriſte, and theſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition muſte they folowe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abyde they not by the Texte, but ſeke ſtartinge holes and bypathes, for yf they woulde abyde onely by
<pb facs="tcp:4167:26"/>the Texte, they were conuinced. For this ſayenge concludeth to ſtronge, that this ſeed of Danid, is a very true and naturall God, for he ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name, whereby the very ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge God is called.</p>
            <p>In the ſeconde boke of Moyſes Exodi.
<note place="margin">Ex. xxij</note> xxij. Are the Iudges called Elohim, Goddes, for their offices ſake, becauſe that they ſitte in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſtede, and are Goddes miniſters: In lyke maner are alſo all Chriſtians called Goddes, as Chriſte, oute of the .lxxxij. Pſalme,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. lxxxij.</note> in the .x. of Iohn maketh reherſall, where as he ſayde vnto the Iewes: Is it not written in youre lawe, I ſayde, ye are God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. But this worde, Iehouah ſhalt thou ſynde no where appropriated to any other, but onely to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maieſtie. The other names, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God alſo is called in the Hebrewe language, as the Iewes ſaye them ſelues, haue ſome occaſion of any worke whiche God doeth. As Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>had,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:26"/>is he called of the feare, that he is feared with all: And ſo did Iacob ſweare by the feare of his Father. Item God is alſo called, Schadai, becauſe he preſerueth and prouideth all thinges, and as the other names be called in their degrees: So that euery name bringeth a worke with it whiche he doth, whereof alſo he is named. Euen as we ſaye alſo, and call hym a God of truethe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becauſe, that he is true, yea he is the trueth hym ſelfe, and maketh men true vprighte. Item a faithefull God, that he is faythfull, and kepeth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he promiſeth.</p>
            <p>Item a God of Peace, a God of pacience, a God of conſolation, as Sayncte Paule doth often name hym accordinge as occaſion is geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym in the mater whereof he doth intreate. But of this name, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is called, Iehouah (ſaye the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes them ſelues) is nome occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, to be declared, neyther is there any worke expreſſed, whereof he is ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4167:27"/>called, but onely that it compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the bare God, hedade and the Godly Mayeſtie. And therefore when the Iewes reade this Texte, they reade not Iehonah, but Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay.</p>
            <p>Thus may we Chriſtians here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſayenge of Ieremie confortably conclude, that Chriſt muſt be knowen as a very and naturall God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs marke diligently this texte,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> that when heretykes and Sectes ſhall aryſe, and aſſaulte this Arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of oure faythe, that Chriſte is not a very and naturall God (as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly this hereſye will come) that we then maye be furnyſſhed, and ready to daſſhe them in their teethe with this ſayenge, agaynſte the whiche they ſhall not lightely be able to brynge vp any thinge. Vvith ſuche ſtronge and ſure argumentes and ſayenges muſte they be taken and conuinced, or elles they will eſcape vs, and gette awaye through euen as the fyſſhes eſcape through the nette. For an heretike is a ſlyppery mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:27"/>whiche can not eaſely be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for he is very uymble in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piures. Wherfore he muſte be ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled in the Godly ſcriptures. All the occaſion hereof is that they preferre their owne Imagination in the ſcripture, and that the ſcripture muſte be iudgeth after their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taſyes and after their owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and muſt be bent and wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted after their owne braynes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought te heare Goddes word with feare, and handle it with humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and not to fall into it with oure owne Imaginations. Thou mighteſte rather fall into all maner of ſynnes, then into thyne owne phantaſticall I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> ſuche a daungerous and noyſible thinge is it. For the worde of God is not to be geſted with all, yf thou canſt not vnderſtand it, then take of thy cappe for it. For it ſuffereth no ſcorues, nor any mannes interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but it is an earneſte matter, and it will be honoured and remembred: And beware whatſoeuer thou doeſt, thou fall not into it with thyne owne
<pb facs="tcp:4167:28"/>Imagination, for yf thou come into it with thyne Imagination, thou ſhalt ouerſhute thy ſelfe as oure Spirites of errour haue done, and knowe not whether thou arte behynde or before in it, and it ſhall be harde for the to geſſe it: For when any man falleth into his owne Imagination, the ſame can not lightely be holpen oute of it agayne.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo happened it alſo vnto the Iewes, they could not perceyue it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they yet at this day perceyue it, that Chriſte ſhoulde be a naturall very God, for they be hardened, and captyues of the deuil, which doth kepe them ſurely in his power, they haue eares and heare it not, and they haue eyes and ſe it not: Euen as Eſaye in the .vi.
<note place="margin">Eſa. vi.</note> Chapiter hath prophecyed of them.
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> And ſo hath it happened vnto all heretykes, when the trueth hath ben layde before them ſo cleare and euident that they myght perceyue it playnely, yet for all that woulde they not ſe nor vnderſtande it. Euen ſo do alſo all Sectes and heretykes, as
<pb facs="tcp:4167:28"/>many as there be of them, they will not be perſwaded, though it ſtode neuer ſo cleare in the Scripture. Is not this the deuill, that a man can not heare, nor ſe that thinge whiche ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before hys eyes? But this is it,
<note place="margin">Pſal. cix</note> that the .cix. Pſalme ſayeth. It is gone through their mary and bones lyke oyle, and lyke water into their bowel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, when thou haſte dronke water and it is chaunged into thy fleſſhe and bloude, then brynge it oute yf thou cauſte. Lykewyſe with the oyle, when it is flowen into any thinge it can not eaſely be taken oute agayne. Euen ſo goeth it alſo with Sectes and hereſies and with oure Imaginations, when this diſeaſe is rooted in, then may the deuill plucke it oute, for I can not. Therfore ſpeaketh Saynet Paul well vnto Titus. Chapter .iij.
<note place="margin">Tit. iij.</note> A man that is geuen to hereſie, after the fyrſte and the ſecond admonicion auoyd, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bringe that he that is ſuche, is peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſynneth euen damned by hys owne iudgemente. Therefore beware
<pb facs="tcp:4167:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:30"/>of Sectes, It is eaſy to come into them, but it is harde to come oute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, beleue me thou canſt not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely come oute agayne, as thou wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in. All this haue I ſayde becauſe of the Iewes, whiche by this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſte Texte will not be perſwaded, that Chriſte is a naturall and very God.</p>
            <p>More ouer it can not be ſayde that God doth participate this name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym, as vnto men, as it is written in the fyrſte boke of Moſes.
<note place="margin">Gene .i.</note> Gene .i. Let vs make man in oure Image af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oure lykenes, but that man ſhould be called a very naturall God, that can not be, for God ſpeaketh in Eſaye Chapiter .xlij.
<note place="margin">Eſa. xlij</note> my glory will I geue to none other. But this name geueth he verely vnto this man Chriſte, the ſeede or braunche of Dauid. Vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath ſpoken before, becauſe that he is alſo a naturall God. And therefore ſpeaketh the one Lorde of the other Lorde, that is, one very naturall God, of another very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall God (for the Prophete ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:4167:30"/>hereof two perſons) and ſayth, I Lord and very God, wil rayſe vp vnto Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid a braunche, which alſo ſhal be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lorde, and very God. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto is requiſite a fayth, which maye comprehende theſe thynges. There is yet, as I haue ſayd, an hereſye to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, agaynſte thys Article of our faith that Chriſt is a very &amp; naturall God, God graunte that we do not lyue ſo longe.</p>
            <p>Furthermore ſayth the Prophete that thys ſede of Dauid ſhall alſo be called, oure ryghteouſnes, The fyrſt name, that he is called Lorde, is concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng hys Godly perſon, whereof he geueth nothynge, neyther doth he par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticipate any thynge thereof vnto vs. But the other, that he is called oure ryghteouſnes, is as touchinge hys of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, wherewith he miniſtreth vnto vs, For in thys name, is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hys hole offyce, and the fruyte or commoditie of thys Kynge. We haue ſuche a Kynge, whiche is very God, and not onely very God, but he is per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynyng vnto vs, For he is oure righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.
<pb facs="tcp:4167:31"/>Thys is oure greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, that thys Kynge and Lorde is oures. And he is become oures, through the humanite, whiche he toke vpon hym, to thintent, that he ſhoulde care for vs as for hys own fleſſh. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che names ought to be written with golden letters, yea not onelye with golden letters, but alſo with druppels of bloude in the botome of the herte. Here ſeeſt thou, that thys Kyng Chriſt is not onely God, but alſo our rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, or oure iuſtification, whiche maketh vs iuſte and ryghteous, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Paule declareth in many places, and ſpecially to the Corith.
<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> i. Corint. i. whereas he ſayth, Chriſte, of God is made vnto vs wyſedome, and alſo ryghteouſnes, and ſanctifyenge and redemption.</p>
            <p>I haue ſayd ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes, that a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten lyfe, ſtandeth in theſe two poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Fyrſt, that our ſynnes, whiche we haue committed, are quyte, and cleane forgeuen &amp; remitted vnto vs through Chriſte, whan I beleue in hym. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarely, that not onelye our ſynnes
<pb facs="tcp:4167:31"/>be remitted, and haue obtayned a righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes, but there is alſo a ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge from the remnaunt of ſynnes, ſo that the remnaunt of ſinnes can not hurte me, for Chriſte is there preſent, the mooſt perfecte ryghteouſnes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is hole ryghteous and pure, and clenſeth me alſo from the ſynnes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che yet remayne in my fleſſhe, for this ryghteouſnes of Chriſte is myne, and is counted to me, ſo that I am without ſynne, not of my ſelfe, but becauſe of the ryghteouſnes of Chriſte. Nowe when I beleue in Chriſte, then muſte Chriſte with his ryghteouſnes ſteppe forth before the face of God in heauen and make anſwer for me. Therfore ought we and muſte, repute hys righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, as though it were oure ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and be ſo bolde thereon, as on oure inheritaunce. For theſe wordes, that he is called oure ryghteouſnes, and no geſtes.</p>
            <p>Now behold what rycheſſe a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man hath, which can neuer dye,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> for he hath CHRIST hymſelfe, what wyll nowe death or ſynne preuayle
<pb facs="tcp:4167:32"/>agaynſt a Chriſten man at the houre of hys departynge?
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Nothynge, death is a laughinge ſtock for hym, he doeth alſo care nothynge for ſynne, for ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſynne, nor death, neyther deuyll nor hel is able to bryng vp any thyng agaynſt Chriſte, whome a Chriſtian hath vp hym. Therfore when death cometh to a faythfull Chriſtian, then ſayth the Chriſtian, Ye are welcome good Syr death, what good newes with you? what ſeke ye here? knoweſt thou not, whome I haue by my? Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte is my ryghteouſnes, I pray the go to and take her from me, yf thou doeſt take her from me, then wyl I folowe the, but thou ſhalt not be able to do it, And ſo do the Chriſtians defye death, and ſpeake with ſayncte Paule, i. Cor. xv.
<note place="margin">i. Co. xv</note> Death where is thy ſtynge? Helle where is thy victory? And as he ſaith in another place.
<note place="margin">Philip. i</note> Philip. i, Chriſt is to me lyfe, and death is to me aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, yf I dye, I haue aduauntage, for I come ſo muche the ſooner to lyfe. There ſeeſt thou, what death preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth agaynſt the Chriſtians, he is now
<pb facs="tcp:4167:32"/>theyr aduauntage, they loſe nothynge by hym, but he byteth hymſelfe to death vpon them.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo goeth it alſo with the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, which is yet remaynyug,
<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet vnto vs, ſhe can not hynder vs, neyther can ſhe damne vs, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte is by vs, which clenſeth and pury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth vs, ſo that we from day to day, become more holyer and holyer, and the longer we lyue, the more enemyes we become vnto ſynne, and ſo deſyre to dye, longynge for the ſaluation, and after the lyfe euerlaſtyuge, This is oure ſanctification. Therfore, whyleſt Chriſtes righteouſnes is oures, ſhe is not ydle, but clenſeth and purgeth vs, as longe as we lyue in thys worlde, vntyll that we alſo be pure and holy, as Chriſte is holy, But all thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from hym.</p>
            <p>And thus hath the Prophete by theſe wordes declared the offyce of Chriſte, namely, that he is our Kyng,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> our Byſſhop or Prieſt, and our rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and alſo oure redemer &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuerer from ſynne, death, deuyll, and
<pb facs="tcp:4167:33"/>hell, and that he delyuereth vs oute of al tribulations, and that he is our lyfe and health and ſaluation. Therfore when I haue hym by faythe, then can the hole worlde, inuente nothynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt me, nor hurte me in any thyng, for he is to great, and ſitteth on the ryght hande of God, where alſo he ſhall remayne howe ſoeuer ſaith nay. Let me ſee, yf any man can thruſte hym downe from thence. He hath good holde, let vs alſo take good holde vpon hym and on hys ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, than ſhall we not nede to feare. It followeth further nowe in Ieremye,
<q>And therfore beholde, the tyme cometh (ſayth the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) that it ſhall be no more ſayde, the Lorde lyueth, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che brought the children of Iſraell oute of the lande of Egypte. But the Lorde ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, whiche brought forth,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:33"/>and led the ſeed of the houſe of Iſraell oute of the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and from all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where I haue ſcatred them, and they ſhall dwell in theyr owne lande agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophete wyll forgette no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge at all. But wyll very rounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and thorowly teache exactely, what is to be preached in the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and wyl ſaye thus: It were not ſufficyent, althoughe thys were preached euen as ye haue heard it, for there myght peraduenture yet be founde ſome weake conſciences, that woulde yet hange vpon the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and beleue theſame, Thoſe doeth the Prophete here preuente, and ſpeaketh of the Chriſtian liberte, and doth hole abrogate and diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulle the olde Teſtament, for he wyll teache a newe, And the newe can not
<pb facs="tcp:4167:34"/>be taught, excepte the olde be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate as the Epiſtle to the Hebrues ſayth in the viij.
<note place="margin">He. viij.</note> Chapiter. As though the Prophete woulde ſaye. There ſhal aryſe a newe preachynge, The olde Teſtament ſhal be no more allowed in the newe Teſtamente, but it ſhall reaſſe, and be abolyſſhed, Thys wyll the Prophete in thys laeſt ſayeng.</p>
            <p>And thys is nowe the doctryne that we teache, and whiche we haue receaued of Paule, namely that amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Chriſtians, there ſhoulde be no lawe or commaundement outwarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for thus ſayth he vnto the Galathi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans.
<note place="margin">Gala. ij</note> ij. I through the lawe am dead to the lawe, That is, throughe the newe lawe in the newe Teſtamente, am I dead to the olde lawe in the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. Moſes is no more alowed with me, ſence I haue Chriſt. The olde Teſtament containeth that the Iewes were bounde to kepe the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whiche God gaue vnto Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vpon the mounte Sinay, namely, howe that they ſhoulde kepe the holy dayes or feaſtes, how that they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:4167:34"/>dwell in them, and in the lande, howe they ſhoulde ordre them ſelues concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng meates and rayment, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer there were more of ſuche lawes and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſo that al their doynges were comprehended, and bounde to certayne perſonnes, tyme,
<note place="margin">Nota.</note> place, and appearaunce, So that they had a politike rule, euen as other regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and realmes haue theyr ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces ſtatutes and lawes, as the Saxo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue the glaſſe of Saxon, where after they gouerne and kepe them ſelues, But ſuche a compulſion as the Iewes had, ſhoulde not the Chriſtians haue, for they ſhoulde not be bounde to any lawe, ſo that they muſte do any thyng by compulſyon and ſhoulde be bound to any perſon, tyme, and apparell as the Iewes, but it ſhulde be a free peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple withoute any compulſyon, whiche ſhoulde do al thynges voluntarely &amp; wyllyngly. Therfore ſayth the. Cx.
<note place="margin">Pſa. Lx</note> Pſalm. Thy people ſhal be willynge. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But what is the occaſyon, that the Chriſtians ſhall not be bounde to the
<pb facs="tcp:4167:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>lawe? Thys is the cauſe, for this Kyng is come to ſet vp ryghteouſnes in earth, that is, to make the people righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Nowe yf he wyl make the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ryghteous, what nedeth then the lawe, yf the people were iuſte, and ryghteous, then neded they not to be made ryghteous, he that is hole, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no phiſicion, ſayth Chriſt in the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>For as much now as the Prophete hath ſpaken afore hande,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> that thys Kynge is a iuſte &amp; a ryghteous Kyng, not onely for hym ſelfe, but alſo that he make other iuſt and righteous, then be not we, whiche are in hys kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, bounde to any lawe, neyther haue nede of any lawe to make vs ryghteous, for yf the world were righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould we not nede an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, nor Prince, nor mayer, nor iudge, nor hangeman, nor wheles, nor gallowes, nor fyre, nor water, nor ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arde, nor halbarde, for euery man ſhoulde do willingly of hys owne mynde, whatſoeuer he oughte to do, euen as a man eateth and drynketh
<pb facs="tcp:4167:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>willyngly, and not compelled. But ſeynge ſhe is a ſtable full of wicked perſons, there muſte nedes be lawes and Superyours, Iudges, hangemen ſweardes, gallowes, and whatſoeuer there is more, whereby the euyll doers maye be kepte in awe.
<note place="margin">i. Tim. i</note> For as Paule ſayth, i, Timo. i. The lawe is not geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto a ryghteous man, but vnto the vnryghteous and diſobedient, to the vngodly and to ſynners, to vnholye and vncleane, to murtherers of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and murtherers of mothers, to manſlears, and hooremongers. But in the Chriſtianite, there are they iuſte and ryghteous, euery man doeth, as he oughte to do wyllyngly, and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there is no power or dominion of the one, ouer the other, but there are they al bretheren, and the one ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the other, helpeth hym, delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth hym, and careth for hys neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, as for hys brother, yea euen as for hym ſelfe, I omitte then that the one ſhoulde eudamage the other, or ſclaunder hym, there nedeth neyther Iudge nor hangeman, neyther ſweard
<pb facs="tcp:4167:36"/>nor gallowes, for all thynges are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne brother lyke, for alſo Chriſte was not aſhamed to call vs hys brethren, where as he ſayde vnto Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,
<note place="margin">Ioh. xx.</note> after hys reſurrection. Iohan. xx. Go vnto mybrethren, and ſay vnto them, I aſcende vnto my father &amp; your father to my God, and youre God.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſayth nowe the Prophete here,
<note place="margin">Nota.</note> that at that tyme, whan this iuſte and ryghteous Kynge ſhall raygne, ſhal the lawe of Moyſes ſtande no more in effecte, whiche he expreſſeth with theſe wordes, where he ſayth, It ſhall no more be ſayde, The Lorde ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, whiche brought the chyldren of Iſraell out of the lande of Egypte, for thys was the othe or maner of ſwearyng amongeſt the Iewes, that they ſayde. By the lyuyng God, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che brought vs out of Egypte. Thys is alſo the maner of the ſcripture to ſweare, as we ſe euery where in the Prophetes, whereby they woulde cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye and aſſure the people, that they teache &amp; preache in the name of God, and at hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, as though
<pb facs="tcp:4167:36"/>they woulde ſaye, This is the trueth and Goddes worde, by the lyuynge GOD, or as trulye as the Lord God lyueth, Euen ſo ſhoulde alſo all prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers be ſure, that they myght ſaye, thus ſayth the Lorde, thys is Goddes worde, and when I preache the worde of God, then is it as muche as yf I dyd ſweare. And whoſoeuer is not ſure of thys, and can not ſaye. Thus ſayth the Lorde, the ſame maye ceaſſe from preachyng well ynough, for he ſhall do no good.</p>
            <p>So is nowe thys the meanynge of the Prophete,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> that the olde Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal be no more taught nor preached that it ſhoulde bynde, but onelye for thys intent, that men maye take there out examples of our fayth, whereby we be aſſured that God kepeth hys promyſes. But of hym ſhal nowe be preached, that hath diſſanulled the old Teſtament, and that noman is iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed or ſaued by the lawe, as the Iewes but that Chriſte is onely he, that iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth by hys ryghteouſnes.</p>
            <p>And thys predication, ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:4167:37"/>onelye be preached in Iuda, or in one or two countres, but throughout all the hole world, Summa Summarum, The olde Teſtament ſhall no more be preached, but the newe, ſo that thys ryghteouſnes ſhall be ſpred abroade, throughout the hole worlde.</p>
            <p>Theſe be oure letters and ſealles, that we be a free people, withoutlawe and withoute compulſyon, but onely for the Chriſtians, which knowe how to vſe the Chriſtian libertye, for we maye not do, as the plowemen dyd the laeſt yeare.</p>
            <p>But where be ſuch Chriſtians that vſe the Chriſtian liberte a ryght, that do all thynges willyngly and gladly, that ſo ſerue theyr neyghboure, and make other partakers of theyr goodes and do accordynge as God hath done vnto them? where be they that glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffre the Croſſe? A chriſtian is a ſeldome byrde. There are very fewe that knowe what is the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberte, The mooſte parte do drawe it to the body, and knowe not,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:37"/>that it is a liberte of the conſcience, and of the ſoule, namely, that thou arte not pure nor ryghteous after the herte and conſcience, but yf thou ſhalt be pure and ryghteous, then muſte thou knoweledge, that thou arte made pure and ryghteous by thys Kynge Chriſte IESVS one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the meanes of hys bloud, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the he hath ſhedde for thy vpon the croſſe, thys maketh the free, But the Lawe of Moyſes, and the lawe of the Emperour &amp; other thynges more do not make the free.</p>
            <p>Vvhen I preache thus, then do I not meane that men ſhoulde not obey to the hyer powers, ſerue them, and geue vnto them that whiche is due vnto them, for the Chriſtian liberte is nothynge touchynge the bodye, nor the outwarde behaueoure and conuerſation, but the ſoule, Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whan thou doeſt ſerue or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beye the hyer powers, then doeſt thou euen as muche as thoughe thou dyddeſt geue to a naked man a
<pb facs="tcp:4167:38"/>coatte, or diddeſt fede the hungry, for it is alſo a dede of charite, whiche flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth and ſpringeth onte of fayth, not that thou ſhouldeſt be made ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous through thys worke, but that it de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare thy fayth, Therfore is thys the ſumme, before god ſhalt thou be rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, without workes, without al la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, onely through Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Here ſeeſt thou,
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> howe counyngly and myghtelye, the Prophetes coulde counterfaycte Chriſte and hye kyngdome, to thintent that they would make vs ſure and certayn, wherein our ſaluation conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth. God graſit that we maye ſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende it and beleue it.</p>
            <p>Thankes be to GOD</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:38"/>
            <head>A ſermon of D. Marten Luther, of the kyngedome of Chriſte, oute of the eyght Pſalm. Lord our Lord &amp;c. made at Merſburg the ſyxte daye of Aug. anno 1545.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hys is one of the principall Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the kyngely Prophete Dauid, wherin he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of Chriſte and his kyngdom. And they are no darke wordes, but cleare light and eaſy to vnderſtande. And he deſcribeth the kyngdome of Chriſt on this wyſe, that although it be in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by working, yet is it alſo here beneeth in earth, and in all the worlde, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateth the kyngdom of Chriſt, from the worldely kyngdome, which is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned
<pb facs="tcp:4167:39"/>by worldly kynges &amp; Powers.</p>
            <p>Theſe two kyngdomes are here be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth in earth amonge men, for alſo the kingdome of Chriſte is here beneth in earth among me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But there is a great difference, that notwithſtandinge, that bothe the kyngdome of Chriſt, and alſo of the worlde are here in earth, yet are they ruled &amp; gouerned after an vnlyke ſorte. For the kyng of whome here the Pſalme ſpeaketh, albeit that he haue his kyngdom in earth, yet doth he rule ſpiritually, and after a heauenly faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion: So that although his kingdome be not ſene, as the worldely kingdome is ſene, yet is it hearde, but howe? Out of the mouth of infauntes and ſucking babes haſt thou ordeyned ſtrength, &amp; ſo is the kyngdome of Chriſt, a kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of hearinge, and not of ſeynge.</p>
            <p>For the eyes do not leade and bring vs thither, where as we fynde &amp; learn to knowe Chriſte, but the eares muſte do that, and alſo ſuche eares, as heare the worde, out of the mouth of Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſucking babes. This is not the faſſhion of the worldely kyngdom, for
<pb facs="tcp:4167:39"/>theſame ſtandeth not onely in the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe, but in workyng and by putting in vre, that the good may be defended, and kepte in equitie Iuſtice and peace, and that the vngodly vntowarde and euill may be punyſſhed, that men may alſo labour with their handes, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne goodes &amp; profites, for there ſhal they not rule nor waxe ryche by their eares: For that thou arte made riche, is not done by the eares, but by the eyes and handes, that thou doeſte take it in hande and accomplyſhe it in dede. In thoſe pointes conſiſteth the worldely kyngdome, farre ſegregated from the ſpirituall kyngdome of Chriſt, whiche kyngdom, although it be here in earth yet is it not executed with plowynge, and with our handes. But it conſiſteth in the worde, and is executed through the worde, whiche procedeth furth of the mouthes of Infantes and ſuckinge babes,</p>
            <p>As when thou ſeeſt and heareſt a preacher, preaching the word of God, thorough the whiche by the commaun hemente of Chriſte he pronounceth
<pb facs="tcp:4167:40"/>Repentaunce and forgeuenes of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there ſeeſte thou neither plough nor harrowe. But thou ſeeſt and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that the Preacher onely vſeth the tonge and the worde, and yet not hys owne word but the word of Godwher by Chriſte ruleth here in earth.</p>
            <p>In lyke maner alſo, when we ſe the holy Sacramentes miniſtred, wherein God offereth and geueth vnto vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all our ſyunes, mercy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the lyfe euerlaſtinge: There ſeeſt thou the delyueraunce from ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and death, that thou alſo arte no more deteyned captiue in the kingdom of the deuill, thou doeſte not ſe it, but onely heare it, that it is offered &amp; geuê the with the tonge of the Preacher, thorough the worde.</p>
            <p>Lykewyſe, whan a chylde, is yonge borue into the worlde of father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whiche is a ſynfull byrth, this do we ſe with oure eyes, but whan the Chylde is brought to Chriſte, grafted in Chriſte through Baptiſme, and is borne agayne of newe, waſſhed from ſynne, and is made the Chylde, &amp; heyre
<pb facs="tcp:4167:40"/>of God, then is it borne agayne a new whiche is farre an other byrthe than the fyrſte, whiche we ſe and fele. The ſeconde and newe byrth, which is done through the water, worde, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, is not ſene, there are onely the wordes hearde, whiche yf I beleue I am made the chyld and heyre of God, and fellowe heyre with Chriſte, not of this corruptible lyfe, wherein we are borne, thorough the fyrſt byrth, but of the euerlaſtinge lyfe, not an heyre of money and goodes. Siluer and Gold. But I am made heyre of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and heauenly goodes and giftes of God.</p>
            <p>Of theſe thinges ſe I none, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare the worde, whiche profereth me ſuch goodes, and ſayth, that I ſhall ſo enioye them, yf I do then receyue and beleue it, then is it euen ſo, and I obteyne all whatſoeuer the word doth profer, promiſe, and geue me.</p>
            <p>So do we alſo ſaye in oure Chylder Crede, I beleue in the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. forgeuenes of ſynnes, &amp; the lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge. Theſe are thinges, which we
<pb facs="tcp:4167:41"/>neither ſe nor fele. They are not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with handes, there vnto belongeth no plough, nor other externall worke. But the worde, yf I heare it and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue it, then do I receyue, and obtayue whatſoeuer the worde proferet &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth vnto me: namely remiſſion of ſynnes, and the lyfe euerlaſtinge, for the worde deceyueth not, whatſoeuer it promiſeth, theſame is yea, &amp; cometh ſo to paſſe agayne, whatſoeuer it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth the ſame is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, whoſoeuer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth ſticke to the worde and his promiſes, theſame doth alſo receyue whatſoeuer it promiſeth and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
            <p>Whanſoeuer I fele my ſynnes, and confeſſe them vnto God, and deſyre of a Prieſte, or Miniſter of the worde, abſolution, or remiſſion of Synnes, then doth the Miniſter of the worde laye his hande vpon my heade, and by the commaundement of Chriſt our Lorde he aſſoyleth me quyte from my ſynnes. There do I heare, and ſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but onely the worde, whereby he aſſoyleth me from my ſynues. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:41"/>yf I beleue the worde, as it foundeth, then is it ſure, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it promiſeth vnto me, and I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue through the abſolution, remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all my ſynnes, and knowledge a mercifull God. Here might nowe any man ſaye, they are greate and hygh thinges where of thou ſpeakeſt, yf it were true, how happye were we? that incontinently remiſſion of ſynnes, and all heauenly goodes ſhoulde folowe the worde, yf I heare it and beleue it? Then coulde I no more feare deathe, nor diſpayre for my ſynnes, nor yet feare the deuill. For all theſe thinges are nowe through the worde of abſolu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion taken awaye from me? Yea I ſay, all thoſe thinges haſte thou, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneſte them euen as the worde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth vnto the, yf thou doeſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it with a ſure and ſtedfaſt fayth, and doeſte not doute at all, As ſone as thou begyuneſte to wauer and to doute, then haſte thou alſo and recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſte nothinge at all, we maye not here hauge vpon the ſighte, but vpon the worde, that I beleue it, than
<pb facs="tcp:4167:42"/>do I obtayne it euery whitte. But yf I do not beleue, but will brynge it to paſſe and obtayne it by the ſighte than haue I alſo nothinge, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer nowe, heareth, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth, and marketh this with dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhall eaſely and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one vnderſtande and marke, what theſe two kingedomes, namely the kyngedome of Chriſte, and the kyngedome of the worlde are, what their office is, and wherein they do conſiſte: And what difference there is betwene bothe theſe kyngedo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, namely that although they be, &amp; are gouerned bothe, here in earth, yet doth the outwarde and worldly hyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome conſiſte onely in doinge and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge, whiche requyreth eyes &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. But the kyngdome of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth onely in the hearinge, ſo that I heare the worde, receyue it, and beleue it, namely the worde, which alſo proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the mouthes of Infantes, &amp; is taught &amp; preached by ſuckelinges, yf I do beleue it, I haue all thinges.</p>
            <p>After this ſorte, can no Emperour, Kynge nor Prince rule, for he muſt do
<pb facs="tcp:4167:42"/>ſtwith the dede. Yf I ſhall be ryche, he muſte not geue me wordes, but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and goodes with the dede. For wordes will not helpe the matter. But here, in Chriſtes kyngedome, is it cleane contrarye, for here, although I were excedinge ryche, and had all the goodes of the worlde, yet were they not able to forgeue nor to take awaye my ſynnes, with all their might, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and power, with al the plowes &amp; harrowes, and with all the ſtrenght &amp; power of al the ſubſtaunce and ryches of this worlde.</p>
            <p>Wherfore? and why ſo? I thought, whoſoeuer had money and goodes, po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer &amp; dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, had hadde all thinges? No, not ſo, he is yet farre from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, &amp; the lyfe euerlaſting although he be ryche, and haue greate goodes, and is mightie, for they heare not the word, wherfore they beleue not but ſticke in darkenes, are drowned in couetouſnes, &amp; in the ſubſtaunce of this world, and they regarde not the word nor God hym ſelfe. And wherſoeuer the worde nor God hym ſelfe is not,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:43"/>there is darkenes and the kyngedome of the deuill, out of the whiche, nomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, goodes, power nor dominion, is able to delyuer him. But yf he will be loſed out of the kingdome of darkenes and of the deuill, and haue remiſſion of ſynnes, and the lyfe euerlaſting, which in the kingdome of Chriſt, through the worde is offered &amp; geuen vs frely, then let hym ſticke faſte and cleaue to the worde, heare theſame, receyue it, and beleue it, ſo ſhall he obtayne all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus ſpeaketh the Prophete clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; diſtinctly of bothe the kingdomes not that he doth abrogate and diſanull the worldely and externall kyngdome which conſiſteth in the doyuge and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyenge, but rather doth approue and confirme it: For rulers muſt be had, for to kepe peace, iuſtice, and vnitie, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the good, &amp; to punyſſhe the euill, or elles there ſhoulde be a great diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre in all thinges, therfore doth not the Prophet abolyſſhe theſame outward kyngedome.</p>
            <p>But in the Spirituall kyngdom of
<pb facs="tcp:4167:43"/>Chriſt whan a miniſter of the Church baptiſeth, with wordes and water, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the inſtitution of Chriſte, yf an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and vnbeleuyng perſon do ſe it, he doth langh it to ſcorne, as a folyſſhe dede, in mans reaſon, becauſe he doth neither ſe nor fele, what there is execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, namely that there are preſent, and baptiſe, al the thre perſons of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maieſtie, receyue the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was conceyued and borne in ſynne, &amp; make hym loſe from the kyngdom of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and fette hym in the kyngdome of heauen, wherin is remiſſion of ſynnes Grace, and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>In likemaner alſo, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an vngodly perſon and an infidele ſeeth, a Prieſte ſayenge his handes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſynner, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite herte for his ſynnes ſake, &amp; forge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing ſynne, or aſſoyling him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne he doth alſo laugh it to ſcorne, &amp; would ſet more by it yf a Cronne of ſyluer or of Golde garnyſhed with Perles &amp; precious ſtones, were ſet on a mans heade, this doth an infidell regarde muche, &amp; a thouſandtymes more, then the layenge on of handes, and forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:4167:44"/>of ſynnes, notwitſtanding that it is not to be compared with any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, treaſure of this worlde.</p>
            <p>But a Chriſten man, beholdeth it with other eyes &amp; with another herte, he regardeth not the Golden Crowne, but hath a reſpecte to the word, which he heareth, marketh theſame, and clea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth therevnto, which ſayth vnto hym on this wyſe. Beleue and cleaue vnto the worde, and thou ſhalt lyue for euer and be a Lorde ouer Synne, Lawe, Deathe, Deuill and Hell, albeit that there are yet ſynnes left remaynynge in the, they ſhall not be imputed vnto the, but they ſhall be all couered and quenched for Ieſus Chriſtus ſake the ſonne of God. What can be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vnto vs, then this, that all out ſynnes ſhall be forgeuen, put oute and taken awaye: And beſydes that, ſhall haue a mercifull God, &amp; obtayne euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge lyfe?</p>
            <p>This is wonderfully ſpoken, but thou muſte beleue, then ſhalt thou ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne all theſe thinges, for withoute fayth, doeſte thou continue in ſynne,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:44"/>and in captiuite in the deuills kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But yf thou beleue, thou arte loſe from ſynne, and delyuered out of the kyngedome of the, deuill into the kyngdome of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>And yf here any man woulde ſaye, I haue euen as well a mouth, &amp; ſpeake euen as well, &amp; make wordes, as a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, yet doth not this folow my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that they might delyuer me from ſyn, &amp; ſet me in the kyngdome of God, howe is it then poſſible, that the mouth &amp; wordes of my Curate, ſhoulde haue more efficacie, to geue all the benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aboue reherſed? To this ſhall we anſwer on this wyſe: There is a great diuerſitie betwene thy mouth, and the mouth of a Preacher, betwene thy worde, and the worde of a Preacher, which difference Dauid doth here cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſhewe, ſaynge: Thou haſte anaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced thy prayſe out of the mouth of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes &amp; ſuckinge babes. This is now an other word, than thyne, or my word which cometh by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hym, whiche ſayethe, Ite.
<note place="margin">Math. xxviij. Marci, xvi.</note> Go ye into all the worlde, and preache the glad
<pb facs="tcp:4167:45"/>tydinges, &amp; teach all nations baptiſing them, &amp;c. he that beleueth &amp; is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued, but he that beleueth not ſhall be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. Chriſt Ieſus, the ſonne of God, oure Lorde, which geueth this commaundemente vnto his Apoſtles, and to all miniſters of the Churche of God, biddeth here to ſpeake and to preache, he doth laye a worde in their mouth, which is another word, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy word,
<note place="margin">Eſa. xl.</note> namely: the word of God, which is euerlaſtinge, and endureth for euer, and ſayeth, he that beleueth theſame, ſhall be ſaued, but he that beleueth not ſhall be damned, this worde hath ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertue, to forgeue ſynne, whiche none other worde hath.</p>
            <p>Yf thou now heareſt me, which am a preacher, and heareſt me none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, than euen as thou heareſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, and alſo geneſt none other credence vnto my wordes, then thou doeſte geue to the wordes of another man, then arte thou damned with me, Yf I alſo did preach no more but mine owne worde, as the Pope hath done, whiche hath taught his owne worde
<pb facs="tcp:4167:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>and not Goddes worde, whome we haue alſo hearde as a man, and is ſo hearde yet of many, which all are dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with the Pope, as they that hange vpon the worde yf men. Thus mayeſt thou not heare me, as a man whiche preacheth the worde of men, for yf thou do ſo heare me, it were muche better, that thou diddeſt not heare me at all, lykewyſe alſo, thou mayeſt not heare thy Curate, as a man, that ſpeaketh and preacheth the wordes of men. But thou muſte heare hym, as one that ſpeaketh the worde, oute of the mouth of Infantes, and ſuckelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whiche ſaye on this wyſe: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in the holy Ghooſte, the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke Churche, whiche hath the worde, forgeuenes of ſynnes, the holy Sacramentes, and the right vſe of the Sacramentes. This church preacheth the worde of God, commaundeth to beleue, forgeueth ſynnes, miniſtreth the Sacramentes, vpon the worde, whiche is the ryghte foundation, and the ſure grounde agaynſte the whiche all the Deuills can not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle
<pb facs="tcp:4167:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>there on muſt I truſte &amp; buylde. This is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of Chriſt, whiche he hath left vnto his Churche and felloweſhip: namely, that ſhe in his name and by his commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, hath geuen and left vs his worde, whiche he ſpeaketh and preacheth by oure mouthes, which alſo we ought to heare, receyue and beleue, as his owne worde, where as this is done in ſuche wyſe, there maye it be ſaide. Thou haſt prepared a power for thyne enemies, for to deſtroye the aduerſary and the reuenger.</p>
            <p>This power or ſtrength is prepared &amp; made through the worde, wherby he beginneth his dominion, ſo that whan ſynne cometh &amp; will byte and deuoure me, that then I maye ſaye. Ah ſynne, ſoft a while, I haue nothing to do with the, neither do I know of any ſynne, for I am made loſe and aſſoyled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne thorough the worde, whereunto I will ſticke. Item, yf the deuill come, and will alſo aſſaulte me, and obtayne the victory ouer me, that as them I maye ſaye, I ſet not by the a ſtrowe. Euen
<pb facs="tcp:4167:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo ſhoulde I alſo ſaye to hell and to death, Oh Death I knowe of no Death, &amp;c. Nowe euen as the worde ſayth vnto the, ſo haſt thou al thynges yf thou doeſt beleue it. But yf thou do not beleue it, thou haſt nothynge neyther doeſt thou obtayne any thing but abydeſt in ſynne, vnder the power of the deuyll, and muſte attende the euerlaſtynge damnation, and death.</p>
            <p>But the Catholyke Churche, which hath thys confort and power, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge, that in comparyſon of the worlde, whiche exercyſeth great and mighty thinges, ſhe is counted for foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhenes and deſpyſed. Yet hath ſhe ſuche great ſtrength and domynion. But whence cometh ſuche great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, &amp; ſtrength, to the poore deſpyſed flocke, the feloweſhyppe of Chriſte? The worldely power geueth her not thys ſtrenght, neyther hath ſhe it to geue. But the worde of God ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thys power, kyngedome, and churche, whiche is ſuche a people, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led here in earth, through the Goſpel, in the vniuerſall Chriſtianite, that
<pb facs="tcp:4167:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath the pure and ſyncere worde, and the ryght vſe of the Sacramentes, &amp; is myghtyer and of greater power, then the Deuyll, Death and hell, and that not in one place, nor in one people But in all the worlde, whereſoeuer the Chriſtians are diſperſed, whiche kyngdome of Chriſte is ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned withoute external compulſyon and violence, and withoute worldely wyſedome, and vnderſtandynge, but onelye through the mouth of infau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten that is, onelye through the worde of fayth, Theſame ſucke lynges and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes are the foules of the worlde, &amp; are deſpyſed. Vvell ſo ſhoulde it be, thys is ryght, ſo ought they to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before the worlde, howe be it, they haue another name before God, and a better reſpecte, They are called prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and Angels of God, and they are ſo in dede. For beholde, what ſayth here Dauid therof, He ſayeth, that the kyngdome of the Lorde Chriſt is ſuch a kyngdom, which ruleth &amp; beareth do minion throughoute al the worlde, not with haruas, Golde, ſyluer, dominy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:4167:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Lordeſhyppes, howe doth he than ſet furth ſuche a great power? on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the worde, which procedeth &amp; is hearde out of the mouthes of the ſucke lynges and infantes,</p>
            <p>For, whan our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, began thys hys kyngedome in thys worlde, he toke not the Emperour of Rome, or the hygh Prieſtes of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, or the beſte, hyeſt, and myghty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt amonge the people, But he toke, poore deſpyſed beggers, poore fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers, as Peter, Andrewe, Iohn, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Thomas, and other poore ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for it, into theyr mouthes dyd he put hys worde, and ſent them furth to preache, whiche notwithſtandynge, that they were called choſen, and ſent of Chriſt, yet were they counted &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fooles before the worlde, But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in what caſe were they on Vvhit ſonday, there dyd theyr power ſhyne &amp; breoke furth, when by the fyrſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of S. Peter, there were thre thou ſande perſons conuerted, &amp; afterward by theyr preachyng many thouſandes were broughte to the kyngedome of Chriſte, then was theyr power ſene
<pb facs="tcp:4167:48"/>and hys power bare rule in Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and amonge the people, of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, vntyl he had cleane gathered out the wheate, then dyd he put fyre in the chaffe, and burned it through the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, Than dyd it appeare, what maner of kyngdome and power Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte had ſet vp. Thys kyngdome &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werdoeth Dauid here boaſte, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth. Thou haſt prepared a power, becauſe of thyne enemyes, &amp;c. And is alſo worthy to be boaſted and magny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed.</p>
            <p>Therfore do we alſo whiche are preachers of the worde, ſuffre greate wronge &amp; iniurye, that we be ſo hated reuyled and abhorred, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge, brynge neytherharnas nor weapen, neyther alſo poyſon, nor any other euyll thynge with vs, But only the ſauynge worde of God, what do we then? or wherewith do we deſerue it? that they do ſo be heretyke vs? what are the great crymes, wherein we do offende? Here ſayſt thou, yea the Pope hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned you with your doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, therfore do we take you alſo forhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retykes
<pb facs="tcp:4167:48"/>and damned. But what can I do withall? I haue not deſerued it, the worde and the doctryne is not my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, yf I dyd it, and yf it were my word then ought it to be condemned and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, as mans worde and doctryne, But nowe is it not my word, neyther is it my doynge, But it is done by the mouthe of ſuckelynges and infantes, through the worde, which is not myne but God hys worde. We bryng with vs a goodly hoolſome doctrine, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goſpell, which offereth and geueth remiſſyon of ſynnes, and the lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge, verely thys is a goodly and louely doctryne, which is none of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but hys that ſent vs, Ieſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes the ſonne of God, yf we ſhoulde ſaye, that ſhe were oures, we ſhoulde do amyſſe, yf we ſhoulde alſo teache &amp; brynge with vs oure owne doctryne, and would leade and inſtruct the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in oure owne wordes, than were we worthy to be counted for heretikes condemned, and put to death for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes, and no iniurye ſhoulde be done vnto vs, But whereas we be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:49"/>and muſte be called Heretykes of them, for the hoolſome doctryne of the Goſpell, which we (as ye haue heard) brynge with vs, and yet is none of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, God amende thys, that for ſuche healthfull doctrynes ſake, we muſt be called heretykes and condemned.</p>
            <p>O good Lord, what doeth the word what doth it worke, wherewith doeth it deſerue it, that it is ſo perſecuted. Thys doeth the worde ſpeake and tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, howe thou ſhalt be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſynnes, from Death, from the power of the deuyll, and from hell. Is thys any hurte, or hereſye. I thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte that men woulde haue runne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the doctryne, and the worde, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che teacheth vs, howe we ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered from ſynne, euen to the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ende, thys wyl not men do nowe, but perſecute it, and teache vs to dout in it, and leade vs to many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where we ſhoulde ſeke ſaluation, &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, as that we ſhould go to Vvalſingam, to Vvilſedom to Caunterbury to S. Iames in Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtella, &amp; to many innumerable places
<pb facs="tcp:4167:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>more. Vvhat goo doe shaue men brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte home fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, but a pouche of lether, and a payr of wery legges, had it not ben bitter, and godlyer, that thou haddeſt taryed at home, and had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt exercyſed thyne offyce and voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein thou arte ordeyned of God, and haddeſt hearbe thy Curate, whiche preacheth vnto the, and out of the mouthe of the ſuckelynges &amp; infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, ſheweth the, the ſure &amp; ryght way to ſaluation, where thou mighteſt be ſure to haue remiſſyon of ſynnes for thy wyfe and children ſitte ydell, thou ſpendeſt thy money, and makeſt wery legges, and yet doeſt no good, and at the laſt, thou arte euen as vnſure, yea muche vnſurer of the remiſſyon of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, then thou waſt before.</p>
            <p>Here ſaye they agayne yea but it hyndereth the maſſes, they haue borne muche hitherto, O what hurte is that, although it dyd hurte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che notwithſtandyng it doth not, what harme were it, whan thou muſte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte out of thys world, &amp; dye, what good can than the maſſes do vnto the.
<pb facs="tcp:4167:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>Who abydeth than by the Maſſes? not one,
<note place="margin">Maſſe.</note> they are all gone, bothe they that haue ſayde maſſe, and they that haue hearde maſſe, what doth it helpe the than, that thou doeſt longe holde taſte? for thou muſte awaye, where are they become, that lye aboute and are buryed in the Cloyſters? what good hath the maſſe done to them? what pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite haue they had by her? they haue ben, and abyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the maſſes, but the maſſes haue not abyden by them, for the maſſes are here, but they are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Vvith all oure hartes do we wyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe vnto them ſaluation, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge lyfe, but thou muſte leaue the maſſe, yf not, thou haſte euerlaſtynge hell fyre for it, why wilt thou not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther embrace, receyue, loue, and beleue the worde? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer they haue thys obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and excuſation, that they are poore, &amp; can not otherwyſe gette theyr lyuyng, as he ſayth alſo, they can or wyl not la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure, and they are aſhamed to begge. Vvell, yf thou wilte not in any wyſe haue it otherwyſe, then go thy wayes,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>But I holde me ſelfe to the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, incorruptyble promyſe of the worde, go thou thy waies ſtil with thy temporall goodes, maſſes, prebendes and Canoſyes. Go to, let vs ſee, howe ſure are the Chanous then of theyr re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Prebendes? This is ſure, yf oure Lorde God, of hys mere good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and grace, had not fent vs the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel in Germany, ye ſhoulde haue here by thys tyme, nothynge at all, neyther prebendes nor Canoniſyes to graunt, for they had all ben gone for twenty yeares agone. But not through vs, they nede not to be afrayed for vs, But the Pope had hadde them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye twenty yeares agone. But howe? Fyrſte thorow the Pallia, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, Bulles, and Pardons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Emperoure Maximilian, hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playned ſence aboue meaſure, aboue xlviij. yeares agone, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe by a Pardon toke oute of Douche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande more then foure hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande crounes, whereby they waxed hote &amp; couetous vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the money, &amp; came agayne thre yeres after with another
<pb facs="tcp:4167:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; would fayn haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery day ſo much money for theyr pardon.</p>
            <p>Then, what haue they taken yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oute of the great Mynſters, &amp; Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprikes, and of the great Prelatures Yf I do well remember, they toke eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yere, of the Prouoſtye of Mirtz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, ij. m. crounes, &amp; ſo in other Myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters more, whiche amounteth yerely to a great ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of money. Nowe, what doth the Pope with the money: He ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it to his Meretricibus, Ciuedis, and Chamberlaynes, to this vſe doeth he put it. Vvel to the matter agayne, I ſaye thus, yf the Goſpel had not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, the Pope with hys Romyſh court had aboue twenty yeares agone and more plucked to hym ſelfe al Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Prelatures, &amp; Canoniſyes, ſo that there ſhoulde not haue ben one, in no Byſſhopryke, which the Pope ſhould not haue had to loue, and pulled into hys power. Thorough theſe tittels, ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheners, Chamberlaynes, Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſales, &amp;c. Vvhiche Tytels they do la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure oute, and bye them before of the Pope, for a greate ſomme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>In ſo much that they haue geuen and yet geue for one tyttel, certayne hundreth dueates, yea alſo a thouſand crounes, accordynge as the Tytell is great. For therfore doeth the Pope ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe the two thouſand perſones, whome he calleth hys Commenſales or boor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, whereof he doeth yet kepe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to borde, nor geneth them meat, but onely kepeth them for thys, diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and geueth them the Tytels after that forte, that throughe them he may pull all Prelatures and Prebendes to hym ſelfe, for as ſoone as there is any voyde any where, hys Commenſales are at hande, and begge it, and ſo at the laſt they come al hole to the Pope.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhould it alſo haue happened long ſence (right worſhipful audience) at Merſburg, and in other mynſters, at Magdeburge, Halberſtadt, and Vvirtzburge, the Pope woulde haue trimmed you after the newe guyſe, by his cookes, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berlaynes, &amp; booderers whiche notwithſtandyng are none of hys Cookes, nor Boorderers in dede, yf the holy Goſpell had not preuented
<pb facs="tcp:4167:52"/>hym. For the Pope doeth onelye for thys cauſe (as hath ben ſayd) kepe ſo many perſons about hym, that throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe them he maye drawe and plucke vnto hym, the goodes and incomes of al Churches, all Cauoniſyes and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latures, as it is to be ſene and is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt euen at Rome, where ſo many glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious great Mynſters and Cloyſters are ſpoiled &amp; waſted by the Pope, as of S. Peter and Paule. Item, of S. Agnete, wherin were wel. Cl. virgins or Nonnes, but nowe there is not one left. In lyke maner alſo other cloyſters wherin haue ben many Monkes, are allſpoyled, and dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out, and no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re but one left remayninge therin, and ſo ſtande alſo yet theſame great gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Churches &amp; Mynſters, as emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Barnes, which of a ſuretie are wel ſo great &amp; wyd, or rather greater then thys fayre cathedral church is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in before many men were fed, relieued entretayned, and had theyr lyuing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we is there no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entretayned. Thus were it alſo happened vnto your chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che and mynſter and other Byſſhopry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:52"/>yf the Goſpel had not come, and ſtopped it. Therfore nede not the fault to be put in the Goſpel, that Byſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rykes, Canonicales, &amp; cloiſters are diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolued, but in the Pope.</p>
            <p>And this is ſure, yf the Byſſhoppes wil not deſiſte, but ſtyl hang vpon the Pope, and the Romyſhe courte, they ſhal depreſſe, and deſtroye al Byſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rykes, but yf they woulde take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a goodly Chriſtian reformation, ſo that the Byſſhoppes dyd preache the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and Chanons dyd ſtudye, and did rede in the mynſters, to their vycares, and to the yong gentilmen, which dyd lyue in the mynſters, than myght they wel continue. And why ſhoulde not men rather kepe ſuche Prelatures and Chanoneryes in our owne countrie then to ſuffre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be plucked away?</p>
            <p>The Byſſhoppes, yf they woulde themſelues, might ſoone fynde a good remedy for this matter, yf they would take counſail, and heare the mouthe of infantes, oute of the whiche the Lorde hath prepared a power for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But thys do they not, but they ſtudye and
<pb facs="tcp:4167:53"/>counſayll, howe they may ſhede much bloude. And why ſo? becauſe they take vs for heretykes, what maner of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes are we then?</p>
            <p>¶ Euen ſuche herelykes are we, that preache the Goſpel, repentaunce and remiſſyon of ſynnes, and teache, howe we ſhal be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne, and made ſafe, &amp; obtayne euerlaſtinge lyfe. Thys hereſye, as they call it, do we teache. Oh good Lorde is thys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll? Ought men for thys to deſtroye, and to ſhede bloude? Vve are no here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes, but preache the holpe Goſpell ſyncerelye and purely, And yet do we fynde with great ſorowe &amp; ſmartes, that they do ſo cal vs, and ſeke to ſhede our bloude, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng that thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke nor meane none euyll, but woulde fayne helpe, and beſtowe our counſail mooſt earneſtly and faythfully in it, that ſuch gorgious Imperial mynſters Canoniſyes, and Prebendes, myghte not be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the haynous hores and fornicatours of Rome. But that they myght be tourned to the good &amp; ryght vſe, wherevnto they were fyrſte myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:4167:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; geuen.
<note place="margin">Maſſe.</note> But here is one thyng in thy waye agayne, namely the maſſe which thou wouldeſt fayn maintayne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Alas, what is the maſſe? Let go what ſoeuer wil not avyde, thou diddeſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer willyngly ſay maſſe before, this is ſure, and I knowe it by me ſelf, which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding haue ben a holy freer, and haue miſerably and pitefully blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemed my Lord Ieſus Chriſt for the ſpace of xv. yeares with my maſſyng, &amp; yet I dyd neuer ſay maſſe willingly, howe holy &amp; deuoute ſoeuer I was. But take the Bible, in ſtede of the maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, ſtudie &amp; learne the holy Scripture,
<note place="margin">Holye ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> deſerue &amp; kepe thy prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with a good conſcience, thys is better, than that the vngodly Romaynes ſhould take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. I would not nowe take ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande crounes, and ſay one maſſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge then, that thou diddeſt it vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly before, why doeſt thou then hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſo ſore with the maſſe? But yf thou haue a delyte ſtyll to accumulate and gether money and to geue theſame to the Romanyſtes, well, geue vnto them ſtyl, as longe as thou haſte
<pb facs="tcp:4167:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>any thynge, what doeth it hynder me.</p>
            <p>But thys woulde I wyſſhe with al my herte, that ſeynge the Byſſhoppes do nothynge towardes any reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but let al thynges go, and be taken awaye after thys ſorte, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours maieſtye woulde loke to it, and preuent, that yet the Pope myght not plucke all thynges into his handes, &amp; vndo vs in the Douche countries and natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, what doeth he for it? He caſteth a bulle before vs, wherewith he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to the deuil. Thys haue we for our money, and nothynge elles.</p>
            <p>I muſt breake of, I haue gone to farce from the matter, Thus I ſaye: we that are preachers, ſeke nothynge elles, than thys, that the word of God myght ſounde and be taught, oute of the mouthes of infantes and ſuckynge babes, and that vnto thoſe whiche do mynde it and ſtudye it earneſtly, ſuche fayre ſtipendes myght be geuen, and not to the Pope, and hys harlottes, kytcheners, and boorderers, which do nothynge for it at all.</p>
            <p>This is nowthe difference betwene
<pb facs="tcp:4167:55"/>bothe the kyngdomes, wherof Dauid ſyngeth here in the Pſalme, namely, the kyngdome of Chriſte, whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the word, offereth and geueth vs remiſſion of ſynnes, &amp; the lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and is gouerned here on earth, through the mouth of ſuckelynges and infantes. The corporall and worldely kyngedome, will alſo be and geue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame, and gropeth there after, but it is but onely gropinge, and geueth onely occupienge and defence. The kingdom of Chriſt is a kingdom of fayth, which is not ſeue nor felte, but onely hearde: The outwarde and worldly kingdom will be felt. But the kyngdom of chriſt can not ſaye, I fele it, and grope with my fyngers the remiſſion of ſynnes, the lyfe and ſaluation. But it will be beleued. Now foloweth further what maner of kynge there is, in this bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng and ſpirituall kyngdome.</p>
            <p>What is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thou remembreſt hym, and the ſoune of man, that thou regardeſt hym, &amp;c. thou haſt ſubdued al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinges vnder hym.</p>
            <p>Here becommeth the kynge God,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:56"/>and Dauid deſcrybeth the Kynge, our Lorde Chriſte, in thys wyſe, that he be bothe very man, and very God, as is here clerely ſhewed and declared, but yet ſo, that he ſhal ſuffre and dye, and ryſe agayne the thyrde daye &amp;c. He is God. for whatſoeuer is in heauen and erth is ſubdued vnto him. For to haue all thynges vnder hys hande and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, pertayneth onely to God, and not to any maner of creatures. No not to the Angels, which are alſo vnder the dominion of the Kynge oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, vnto whome be laude and prayſe, for euer and euer AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An homily or ſermon of the famous doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Vrbanus Rhegius of fayth and reſurrection, vpon the Goſpell of Mathew in the ix. Chapter, of the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man, whiche was grieued with the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſew of bloudde, and of the doughter of the chief ruler, which being dead Chriſt reſtored to lyfe, prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched to the people of Hannouer in Saxon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Elbeloued in the Lord, whan be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſpace of two yeres, I was called to you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the wyl of God our celeſtiall father, that I might aduaunce your loue and honour dewe vnto God and healthe of your ſoules by teaching, admonyſhing &amp; writinge,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:57"/>I ceaſed not from that tyme to praye vnfaynedly and diligently God oure heauenli father, that he would vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to preſerue you in holſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, true fayth and hope of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to finyſhe his worke, begonne in you. And now I thanke his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goodnes, that he hath preſerued you vnder ſo many temptations, ſtormes &amp; ingines of afflictions and perſecutions and hath fortified your myndes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, and becauſe all your afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and perſecutions haue chaunced to the increaſe and ſtabilitie of your ſanynge hope, through the fatherly goodnes of God and his ſingulare counſayll, that ye may be now more ſtrong and more perfite to a deuoute and bleſſed lyfe in euery exerciſe, than ye haue bene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But forſothe for as muche as the deuil our moſt cruell and moſt ſworne enemye, doth aſſaulte and endeuoure to deſtroye the fayth and doctrine of Chriſte, by diuerſe and continuall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, by merualous wiles, by moſt crafty ſubtilitie, and by many cauteles in euery place and in euery momente,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is neceſſary that ye fortifie your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, and fyght with all your myghte &amp; mayne agaynſte an enemye ſo muche to be feared, takyng quycklie true and vnwynable weapons, and an vnuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſworde, that is to ſay, the worde of God, the worde of ſauyng and eternal veritie, whiche the deuill more feareth and dreadeth tremblyng, than we mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and feble men may be troubled for feare of fyre, of flouddes, of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes, of knyfes, and of ſwordes, of gonnes, and of what other thingeſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer may hurte and deſtroie our corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lyfe.
<note place="margin">Coloſ. ij</note> And therefore Paule admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſheth his coloſſians, that the word of God in habite abundantly in them. For he did knowe and had learned by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that the ſpirite of lienge may ſuffre nothynge leſſe nor more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſlie, than the exerciſe of the pure word of God, by which his counſayls and weapons be made blunte and be broken, by whiche alſo we be fortified in faythe and hope of Chriſt more and more, that we may fyght valiauntly in ſpirituall fyghtyng &amp; battayle, againſt
<pb facs="tcp:4167:58"/>the Lordes of thys worlde, the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures of darkeneſſe of this time, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agaynſt the euyll &amp; crafty ſpirites vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that we may obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne finally a glorious victory.</p>
            <p>For thys cauſe I wolde confirme &amp; confort your charities with ſome ſhort &amp; compendiouſe oration, inſtruction, &amp; admonition, bycauſe I came agayne to you, God ſo gouernyng and willinge. Therfore I wil intreate the goſpell of this preſent day of ſ. Mathew, in the ix. chapter,
<note place="margin">Mat, ix</note> in which ſ. Mathew ſetteth out to vs two notable myracles done of Chriſt, whiche was written of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt to our profyt, that our faith may be ſtirred vp, renewed, quickened fortifyed and preſerued, and that oure charitie may be kendled &amp; inflammed towarde God and oure neyghboure.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt reſtored to health that miſerable woman, which was grieued ſore with a flixe of bloude xij. yeres, &amp; coulde not be healed with any medicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. After he calleth agayne the dead mayd vnto lyfe. In theſe two hiſtories &amp; wiracles of the goſpel, I wil intreate principally alſo two articles. Firſt, for aſmuche as Chriſte doeth commende
<pb facs="tcp:4167:58"/>ſo greatly the faithe of that woman ſayng, beleue, thy fayth hath made the ſafe, &amp; becauſe we knowe that he hath teſtored her, by hys owne propre po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, puttyng away her ſickenes, a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſary queſtyon preſenteth it ſelfe to to vs, which is worthy to be diſcuſſed &amp; declared, that is, wherfore ſcripture at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributeth euery where ſo much ſo faith Chriſt ſaith here, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faith hath made the woman ſafe. In an other place we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de agayn,
<note place="margin">Ioh. iij.</note> that faith bryngeth iuſtice &amp; eternal ſaluation, whan not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge it is manifeſt, that our fayth is yet vnperfite &amp; weake, that we be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrayned with the diſciples to praye,
<note place="margin">Mar, ix</note> Lord encreaſe oure faythe, Vve heare alſo often in theſe tymes, howe vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentlye the blynde world is offended, whan faith vnto Chriſte is publyſſed, &amp; exalted with worthy prayſes. Theſe newe doctoures (ſay they) can no other thing now, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to prayſe &amp; auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t only fayth, whether only faith might do al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynges &amp; ſaue vs? in nowyſe: mo thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges be required tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely faith. For it is neceſſary that works be alſo preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, only faith is not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; is moch we aker &amp; of leſſe power, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it maye
<pb facs="tcp:4167:59"/>do that thing. Doeth not the deuill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beleue, but neuertheleſſe he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned euerlaſtyngely. Theſe be the ſaynges of oure aduerſaries, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it may be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d eaſely, how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they be offended by the prayſes of fayth. But we ſhall heare how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they erre.</p>
            <p>After we ſhall intreate of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, occaſion taken of that, that Chriſt calleth agayn here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lyfe a wenche, now whan her body ſhould haue bene buried, this is truely ſo greate &amp; ſuche a worke, that neither reaſon will nor maye conceyne it, but ſtrong fayth muſt nedes be preſent. It is truely neceſſary, that the holy Ghoſt gyue and preſerue merueloullye that faythe: for it is tempted by meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe and horrible wayes of the world, which iudgeth that fayth to be a mere folyſheneſſe, it is tempted alſo of oure owne propre reaſon, and of the deuyll hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>This Goſpell perteyneth to two articles of the crede, of oure Chriſtiane faythe, that is to ſaye: to that greateſt
<pb facs="tcp:4167:59"/>article, which maketh vs Chriſtians, I beleue in Ieſu Chriſte his onely ſonne oure Lorde, And I beleue the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body.</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>The fyrſt Article.</head>
               <p>CHriſte prayſeth the faithe of the woman,
<note place="margin">Mat. xv viij. Luc. vij xvij.</note> &amp; he doeth that in many places in the hiſtori of the Goſpel, ther of it may be eaſeli vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that faith ſhuld be publiſhed &amp; exalted with pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; his power &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tli declared &amp; ineulcated: for Chriſt doth prayſe nothing, except it be prayſe worthie. Wherfore, fyrſt I ſhall teache &amp; proue, that the prophetes Chriſte, the Apoſtles &amp; old writters of the right opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; fayth haue preached and publiſhed alwayes fayth after the ſame maner, that it may be ſene, that we be reproued &amp; blamed now vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely for this doctrine. Therfore I will not take it grieuouſly, to put to alſo the cauſe of ſo great prayſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, whereby fayth is prayſed.</p>
               <p>Moſes about to ſhowe how Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham
<pb facs="tcp:4167:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>fyrſt obtained ſo great grace of god, that god reputed him to be iuſt, &amp; confeſſed, that he was his well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, whiche ſhoulde be heyre of the worlde, and of whome he wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de begod,
<note place="margin">Gent. xv.</note> ſayeth in this wiſe. Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleued in god (vnderſtande thou in the promiſes of god) and it was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him to iuſtice, as Paul conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth &amp; declared diligently and exactly theſe wordes of god.
<note place="margin">Rom. iij. iiij. Mal. iij.</note> Rom. 3 &amp;. 4 alſo galat. 3. I beſeche you, is it a light and litle matter, that Abraham was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iuſt before God for his faith? here ſurly ſaith vnto the promiſes of god is preferreth to al the workes of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by this ſelfe thinge he is declared very euidently to pleaſe almighty god chiefly. Let all the ſortes of monkes, &amp; all the flockes of pahriſeis of our time come out, &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bringe furth ſo clere and euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimony of the ſcriptures to the glorifycation and confyrmation of their humane workes.</p>
               <p>In the ſero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d boke of par ali. 20. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kinge Ioſaphat was in great peril, the Moabites, Aminonites &amp; Edomites
<pb facs="tcp:4167:60"/>cominge at hande: to him great ſpede, and whan he might notwithſtande by the ſtrengthe and power of his people ſo great a power and violence of his ennemies, and all Iuda being abaſhed for that, the propher Iaſihel ſaid, drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not &amp; feare not this multitude, but onely ſtande boldly, and ye ſhal ſee the helpe of the lorde vpon you. Beleue in the lorde your god, &amp; ye ſhal be in ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fegarde, beleue to his prophetes, &amp; all thinges ſhal chaunce proſperouſe, And whan the people did ſynge praiſes to god in faith, the lorde turned the wiles and crafte of their enemies againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes for the ſonnes of Ammo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab did ariſe togither againſt the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, and afterwarde they did ſlea &amp; deſtroye thier ſelfes by motual diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, but al the people of Iuda &amp; their king hauing the riche ſpoile &amp; ſo great a fortune, rei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed excedingly. This ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample is ſurely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted and writen alſo to vs, vnto our profit that we may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that faith pleaſeth god, &amp; that the ſelfe faith leadinge to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of GOD ouer cometh and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth victory, And that it may all
<pb facs="tcp:4167:61"/>thinges with God, &amp; thoſe thinges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo which ſeme to men to be impoſſible.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde Pſalme ſayth:
<note place="margin">Pſal. ij Ier. xvij</note> bleſſed be all men whiche truſt in the Lord. Yf they be bleſſed which truſt to god in his worde, ſuerly it is neceſſary that fayth is no little thinge before God, for as much as it promyſeth bleſſing to them that beleueth in him.</p>
               <p>Alſo the .xxx. Pſalme ſayth:
<note place="margin">Pſa. xxx xxv. lxx.</note> I truſt in the O Lord, I ſhall not be confounded for euer. Let no man meruayle that I bring ſentences of hope to my purpoſe &amp; inſtruction for hope &amp; faith in Chriſt be ioyned together, and may be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by thought, but this is ther nature that they be alwayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned &amp; vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions. For whatſoeuer I be leue of the promiſe of God, &amp; therfore not yet do I ſee it (for that which is ſene is not beleued) I truſte that, that ſhall come &amp; be here after, &amp; I loke for that to be here after ſomtime. Moreouer that word which Dauid vſeth here, that is, Thaſah, ſignifieth alſo to truſte. We know of Pau. in the iij. &amp; iiij. chapters to the Rom. that without al controuerſy,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:61"/>faith by it ſelf is that truſt in Chriſt, or that ithath that truſt conioyned &amp; anne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>xed.
<note place="margin">Eſa. liij.</note> Eſaias in the liij. chap. teacheth that we are iuſtified by counynge &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Meſſias: but that connynge is no other thinge than faythe in Chriſte which we take by chriſt of the promiſe of God. Therfore Eſaias teacheth vs that ſame thing in that chapter, whiche Paule teacheth in the iij. and .iiij. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Romaynes, and in the .iij.
<note place="margin">Rom. iij iiij. Gal. iij.</note> and in the .iij. chapter to the Galatians, that fayth in Chriſte maketh vs iuſt.</p>
               <p>Ieremi. xvij. bleſſed is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which truſteth in the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ier. xvij</note> and whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhall be the Lord. Iere. v.
<note place="margin">Iere. v.</note> Lord thy eyes loke vpon fayth. The worde which the interpreter tranſlateth here, fayth, is in the Hebrue Emunah, which alſo Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome noted, And that worde ſignifieth truth and truſte, whan a man doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing faynyngly, nor of hypocriſye, but erneſtlye and of good wil and courage that he may cleaue to with full truſt of harte and conſtante, taythe to the moſt true promiſe of God, whiche can not deceaue, lye and diſapointe. We know
<pb facs="tcp:4167:62"/>truely that whan god turneth ſo his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes or face any where, he ſhe weth not indignation and wrathe, but grace and faith, as faithfull fathers haue their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes fyred vpon their children with the moſt inclined and ardent affection of harte, that they may kepe them, their harte alwaies fyxed thider, whither their eyes be directed.</p>
               <p>Therfor faith is an pleaſan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te &amp; ſwea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſacrifyce in the eyes of god, and the trew worſhippinge whiche he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euery where in ſcriptures. The texte ſath in the .6.
<note place="margin">Daniel. vi.</note> chapter of Daniel Daniel was brought furth of the lake &amp; no hurte was founde in him, becauſe he beleued his god. Seeſt thou not that faith obtaineth alſo victori wher battal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le is begonne with moſt cruell lyons? the lorde ſaith in the ſecond of Oſeas,
<note place="margin">Oſee. ij.</note> ſhal be trouth ſhe to me in faith forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the this is the greateſt &amp; trueſt praiſe of faith, that it is the betruthinge and weddinge ringe, with which we be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyaunced to god, as his moſt pleaſunt ſpouſe, that we may receiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4167:62"/>of all his goodnes with him.</p>
               <p>Habacurk in the ſecond chapter,
<note place="margin">Haba. ij</note> the iuſt man ſhall liue by faith. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete ſpeaketh not here of this corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lyfe, whithe alſo the wicked and miſſheuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue, yea and the bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te beaſtes, but of the true lyfe, by whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we lyfe before god in grace, as wel beloued ſounes of god, which ſurely ſhall entre vnto eternall lyfe, as hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to the father, after this tranſptory and ſhortely decayenge lyfe, in whiche heires Chriſt lyueth here, and leadeth ruleth, and gouerned them with hys worde and ſpyrite &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now let vs ſee what chriſt and his diſciples ſaye of faith in the newe teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament.
<note place="margin">Math. viij.</note> In the 8 chapter of Mathew chriſt ſayth to Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turio, like as thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueſt ſo be it to the. In the .9.
<note place="margin">Math. ix.</note> chapter of Mathew, whan chriſte had ſene the faith of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſycke in the palſey and theyr faith which brought to chriſt the man taken with the palſey, lyeng ſyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in a bedde, he did forgeue to hym hys ſyunes and reſtored hys healthe
<pb facs="tcp:4167:63"/>to him.
<note place="margin">Mat. xv</note> In the .xv. chapter of Mathew, Chriſte cryeth, woman, thy faythe is greate,
<note place="margin">Matth. xxi.</note> be it to the as thou willeſte. In the .xxi. chapter of Mathew, ye ſhalres ceyue all thinges, whatſoeuer ye bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhal aſke in your prayer. In the ix. chapter of Marke,
<note place="margin">Mar. ix Luce. vij</note> to men beleuing all thinges are poſſible. In the .vij. chapter of Luke, the Lord ſayth to Magdalent thy fayth hath mayd the ſafe, go thou away in peace.
<note place="margin">Luk. viij</note> In the .viij. chap. of Luce Chriſt ſayth to the chief man of the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagog: feare thou not, beleue thou one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thy doughter ſhalbe ſafe. In the xvij. chap. of Luke,
<note place="margin">Lu. xvij.</note> Chriſte ſayth to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> full of lepry, which he made cleane, ryſe you vp, go thou awaye, thy fayth hath ſaued the. So he ſayde alſo to the blynde man in Hiericho.
<note place="margin">Lu. xviij</note> In the xviij. chap. of Luke Faith is called the gyfte of God, And through the holy Goſpel of Iohn, God promiſeth euerlaſtinge lyfe to them that beleue in Chriſte. In the xv. chapter of the Actes,
<note place="margin">Act. xv.</note> Peter tea cheth that fayth purifieth our hartes. And in the xvi. of the Act.
<note place="margin">Act. xvi</note> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par of the priſon ſayth to Paul &amp; Sila,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:63"/>Maiſters what thing muſt I do, that I may be ſaued? They anſwered to him, beleue in the Lord Ieſu, and thou ſhalt be ſafe, and thy houſe. And in the xi.
<note place="margin">Hebr. xi</note> Chapiter to the Hebrues, Saint Paul reckeneth furth a greate reherſall of the deuoute and olde Chriſtianes, And he writteth that thei were welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued to God, and pleaſed hym. And that they ſhewed myracles by faythe, and that it maye not be, that any man pleaſe god withoute fayth. How often ſayth Paule, that fayth without wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes iuſtifyeth, whiche thynge the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctours of the church of ryght opinyon and fayth ſetfurthe by theſe wordes: onely fayth iuſtifyeth.</p>
               <p>But for aſmuche as our aduerſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es accuſe vs, and bable, that faythe is prayſed to moche, and exalted aboue meaſure of vs, thereby they ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes not yet to vnderſtande, what is fayth, and what the ſcriptures of the Prophetes, and Euangeliſtes, yea &amp; the fathers and auncient Byſhoppes teache of Chriſtian fayth. Wherfore let no man ſuffre hymſelf to be leadde
<pb facs="tcp:4167:64"/>awaye from the trueth by the rebukes of oure aduerſaryes, by whiche they ouerthrowe vs.</p>
               <p>That not any man may be troubled lightly, and called away from the true ſentence, we ſhall ſhewe the cauſes wherfore ſcripture prayſeth and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſo greatly faith in Chriſt. Faythe in vs is vnperfite, &amp; euereaceth from day to day, &amp; for that cauſe it is not ſo perfite a work by it ſelfe, that ſo great thynges may be attributed and gyuen for the perfection of it ſelfe. But the couſe of thys laude and prayſe is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe fayth gyueth true glory to oure Lorde God, and becauſe it beleueth, that he is mercyfull, iuſte, &amp; true, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wil &amp; maye performe ſurelye hys promyſe in Chriſt. Thys is the ryghte &amp; true worſhipping of God, Vvhoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleueth, ſo the word of God, he calleth vpon God in all hys neceſſite without doubte, &amp; truſteth &amp; loked for help of him in patience. Therfor faith is theſame thyng, which cleaueth &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth it ſelf to true perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to ſay, to Chriſte, &amp; apprehendeth the mercy of god promyſed in Chriſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:4167:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>promyſe may not be apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; taken otherwyſe by no other meane or inſtrumet, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faith, which is a truſt vnto the promyſed grace &amp; help of god in Chriſt in al miſeries &amp; neceſſities. If it might be, that I had al the works of al men, &amp; I had not this faith, I myght not yet apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the promyſe in chriſt by al theſe workes. This is the nature of the promiſe, that it deſyreth to be ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehended by fayth. God promiſeth to vs al help &amp; grace for Chriſtes ſake, wherforyf I ſhuld make leane, &amp; amoſt kyl my ſelt the ſpace of an hole yeare by moſt ſtrayte &amp; greuous faſtynges, eatyng nothing, but cruſtes of breade, &amp; drinking pure water, &amp; yf I ſhuld go on pilgrimage to Rome armed &amp; fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on al partes, or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my bare fete, not clothed with ſynnyng clothe, but with a wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; rough garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, rubbing &amp; prickyng my ſkynne, yet I myght ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer apprehend the promyſe of God in Chriſt by they works how painful ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thei be. But wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I heare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God promyſeth &amp; offereth to me hys mercy &amp; help, and whan I truſt to hys worde as true &amp; almygtye, &amp; I beleue to God
<pb facs="tcp:4167:65"/>whiche can not lye and deceaue, than I apprehende and receyne theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by that fayth, whiche he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed in Chriſte. Therfore the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of true opinion and faythe doth declare, openly not withoute a cauſe that onely fayth &amp; not any work iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth &amp; ſaueth. For becauſe the Goſpel ſheweth, offereth &amp; gyueth to vs Ieſu Chriſte the Sonne of God, whiche alone and no other hath delyuered vs from ſynne and death, howe may thou receyue otherwyſe hym, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in thy harte hym as thyne owne propre, than by onely fayth in hym, that thou mayeſt beleue to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that is to ſaye, that he hath dyed and ryſen agayne for the, and that he is trnely thy ſauyoure and delyuerer.</p>
               <p>Vvherfore note ye diligentlye and forgette not, that true fay the in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte is onely the true meane and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which we laye hande on, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende and receyue the mercye of God promyſed to vs in Chriſt, and al benefytes to our ſaluation. But whan we heare that faith is greatly prayſed
<pb facs="tcp:4167:65"/>let vs not thinke that there is ſuche a perfection in vs, whiche hath deſerued ſo great teſtification in wordes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures and prayſes. For it by it ſelfe deſerueth not that, but it is the truſt in the mercy of God by Chriſte. Therfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouer thoughtes muſt be anone directed vnto Chriſte, vnto whome faythe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth it ſelfe, to whome it faſteneth and conioyneth it ſelfe, to whome it clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and for whoſe cauſe it loketh for and receyueth all good and healthfull thynges of God. Faythe is alwayes vnperfyte, but Chriſte to whome faith afflixed cleaue to, is not vnperfite, but the true, infinite, and vnmeaſurable treaſure of all perfection. Yf folyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is with vs, Chriſte is oure wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Yf we haue ſynne, Chriſte is our iuſtice, Yf we be not enduwed yet with that holines, with which we ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be, for the cauſe of oure ſynnynge fleſhe, Chriſte is oure ſanctification. And whan we ware yet pryſoners vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tyran of hell to euerlaſtynge death, And whan he had no counſayll nor helpe in the hole world, foraſmuch
<pb facs="tcp:4167:66"/>as no creature myghte delyuer vs, and therfor we ſhould hane peryſhed, than God fende and gaue to vs hys owne propre ſonue vnto a redemer, that he myght be oure redemption i. Corinth i.
<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> In concluſyon we haue all fulneſſe in Chriſt, and we haue theſe thynges in hym mooſte ſufficiently, mooſte plenteouſly and moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntly, whiche we haue nede of: And we maye not make propre to vs, and clayme or laye hande on thys treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and gyfte of God by anye other meane, than by tiue fayth, which faith withoute controuerſy is effectual alſo by good workes, becauſe it receaueth the holye Ghooſte, and reneweth and purifyeth the man. No deuyll nor wicked and myſcheuouſe perſon hath thys faythe, albe it they be not verye ignoraunte of the hiſtorye of Chriſte, what hys perſon is, and what is hys ſeruyce, notwithſtandynge they haue not thys confidence of him, that he is theyr redemer, and ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure, and that he wyll delyuer &amp; helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the Deuils know what thing
<pb facs="tcp:4167:66"/>God hath thretened to them, that is to ſaie, iudgement, and moſt ſure damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therfore they tremble and quake. But whan we praiſe ſo greatly fayth, than we ſpeake of true faythe in Chriſt, which is a certayne liuely truſt &amp; hope of the grace of God, whiche he hath promyſed to vs in Chriſte, that is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl forgeue to vs all oure ſynnes for Chriſtes ſake, whiche hath ſatiſfyed for our ſynnes, he wil repute vs iuſte, and he wil gyue to vs eternal lyfe. Neyther the deuill nor hys mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres may haue this fayth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of god, but the choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt haue onely it. And this is that faith, whiche hath reſtored this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which ſhe was made partetaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; help. Thys fayth hath made thys woman the doughter of Chriſt, that he dyd voucheſafe to call her hys dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as Chryſoſtome ſayth. And whan ſcripture prayſeth thys fayth, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace and mercy of god, for this fayth is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meregrace of god pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed for chriſtes ſakerther for thei me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt uede be rude, diſmaied, vnaduiſed
<pb facs="tcp:4167:67"/>yea frowarde and maliciouſe, whiche can not ſuffre, that ye moſt abundaunt grace of God, by whiche we ware de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered from the power of darkeneſſe be prayſed and exalted. See that ye be ware of thys kynde of men, for they be leadde of thatſame euyll ſpirite, whiche blynded once the Pelagianes.</p>
               <p>Let vs ſet before oure eyes, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe alſo here the example of charitie and mercy, which we ſee here in Chriſt Ieſu oure Lorde and God, and that we maye be moued by affection of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie and miſery of our neyghbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, And that we maye helpe and ayde them accordynge to the facultie of our powers and goodes. For fayth ought not to be without fruytes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An other Article of the reſurrection of the dead.</head>
               <p>Here let vs behold &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider with intentyue, eyes bothe the word &amp; work of Chriſt our Lorde. For as moche as they he ſo merueylouſe,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:67"/>that we may neuer meruayle ynough at them, nor neuer prayſe ynough the glory of hys grace. He ſayth that the wenche ſlepeth, anone he toke her ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and calleth her vnto lyfe.</p>
               <p>The worlde hearyng this, ſtandeth by with ſtyf &amp; aſtouyeng eyes, &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mocketh, for it ſemeth incredible and a mere folyſhenes, that a deformed, mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall, colde, ſtyffe, and ſtynkyng caryon ſleapeth. In concluſyon how may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone beleue, that death is not death.</p>
               <p>Auguſtine in the .lxviij. Pſalm ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. We knewe (vnderſtande then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comyng of Chriſte, before the worde of God was publyſhed in the worlde, or before our conuerſyon, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation) in mankynde two thinges but one thing was vtterlyvnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs. That men be borne &amp; dyeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we knowe, but that they ſhal aryſe agayn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, and ſhal lyue euerlaſtyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly, that we knewe not. The miſteries of God be hyd before reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weledge of theſe very greate thynges is not graffed &amp; ſet in the hartes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the lawe of nature, &amp; therfore reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4167:68"/>all philoſophy &amp; worldlye wyſedome myght knowe nothing of that. It was knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt of al by the goſpel of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, which was ſent by the holy ghooſt from heauen vnto earth. Whoſoeuer hath not the goſpel, or beleueth not it, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe nothing of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor of eternal lyfe, which thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blind &amp; ignorant ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, witneſſeth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their writtynges. Therfor ſayeth Paule.
<note place="margin">i. Cor. ij.</note> i. Cor. ij. that God hath reueled &amp; ſhewed to vs theſe thinges by hys ſpirite, &amp; that we haue not receaued the ſpirite of the world, but the ſpirite of God, that we may knowe what thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geuen to vs of Chriſte. A naturall man vnderſtandeth not thoſe thinges, which be of the ſpirite of God it is folyſheneſſe to hym, and he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not vnderſtand it. And we heare that here in the Iewes, which mocke &amp; ſcorne the Lorde, where he ſaith, ſhe is not dead, but ſhe ſlepeth. For they could not per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue and knowe, howe death myghte be a ſlepe. Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for thei ſuppoſed that theſe wordes of Chriſte was dreames of a ſycke man, and mere tryfles and
<pb facs="tcp:4167:68"/>ſaiynges of a madde man. And this is the deſteny of the goſpell alwayes in the worlde, that it is ſuppoſed &amp; called folyſheneſſe .i. Cor. i.
<note place="margin">i, Cor. i.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whan Paul in the .xxvi.
<note place="margin">Ac. xxvi</note> of the Actes teached of the reſurrection of the dead the lieuetenaunt Feſtus iudged that he was madde. How hardly beleued Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas that Chriſt was reuiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dead Iohn. xx.
<note place="margin">Iohn. xx</note> At Athenes they called the ſermones of Paul of the reſurrection a babblynge, although they auaunted that there was the fountayne of al ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſciences, and wyſedome,
<note place="margin">Ac. xvij</note> the xvij. of the Actes. The Sadducees amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Iewes iudged that the ſermones of Chriſte of the reſurrection was a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne tryflyng fable &amp; thynges impoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble. Math. xxij.
<note place="margin">Matth. xxij.</note> And Auguſtyne wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth in the .xxij. boke de ciui. dei. the .v. Chapter. There be thre thinges incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyble, which not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> done. It is incredible y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt hath ryſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayne in body, &amp; hath aſcended vnto the heauens with hys body. It is incre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dible that the worlde hath beleued a thyng ſo incredyble. It is incredyble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4167:69"/>that men of none eſtimaton, feble, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, vnlerned, myght perſwade ſo effectually a thyng, ſo incredible to the worlde, &amp; alſo to lerned &amp; connyng me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in it. The carnal ſonnes of thys world ſuffer not to beleue the firſt point, that is to ſay, that Chriſt hath ryſen again. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d point, that is to ſay, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding hath beleued this thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, although it was incredible, they be conſtrayned to ſee before ther eyes it, foraſmuche as the reſurrection of the dead is beleued ſo ſtedfaſtly &amp; conſtat<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throughout al the worlde of al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therfor they may diſpiſe this lyfe with al his ryches, profittes, plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures, &amp; power, &amp; ſhewe alſo their mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del fynger to death, as Paule doeth. i. Corin. xv.
<note place="margin">i. Co. xv</note> Vvhere is death thy prick?</p>
               <p>The ſonnes of this world ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not fynd or know fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence that other is done that is to ſay, that the worlde beleueth the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except they ſhal beleue alſo the third point, that is to ſay, that it was done by the Apoſtles, men bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyug theyr preachyng &amp; ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Our fayth dependeth not of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:69"/>nor hath cauſes ſet and grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon, as philoſophy or worldly ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but it dependeth &amp; conſiſteth all in the word of God. Vvhat thynges ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer god hath promyſed, he may perfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; no man may let it. The world knoweth nothing of the word &amp; power of God, it beleueth not the firſt article of the almighty power of God, and of the creation &amp; conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, it hath regard onely vpon creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; their mutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, it ſeeth death, but it can ſee nothyng els here, than theſe thynges, which may be apprehended, with corporal &amp; outward ſenſes, that is to ſay, a wenche theyr lyeng, ſtyf, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryble in ſight, deade and deſtitute of al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>her ſtrenghtes: It ſeeth alſo, that ſhe beynge deade, can not helpe her ſelfe, that none in earth can call her agayne vnto lyfe. Reaſon thincketh vpon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, but mannes ſtrenghtes, it can not go further, &amp; therfor it mocketh the wordes of Chriſte. For as al worldely power may not make a creature of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſo it may not rayſe vp agayne a dead man. Therfor yf we loke and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde
<pb facs="tcp:4167:70"/>only ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s power &amp; ſtrenghtes, than our laboure is in vayne, and it is plainly impoſſyble that a dead ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be called agayne to lyfe, &amp; aryſe agayne. Wherfor it is neceſſary that we haue regarde here vnto the diuine power &amp; ſtrenghtes of the creatour, excepte we deſyre to erre and blaſpheme with the wicked and myſcheuous world. Vvho is he that ſayth, the wenche ſleapeth? If I or any other pure tried ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſay theſe wordes of him ſelf, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de there be onely conſolation of the wordes, &amp; nothyng elles. For we may not call agayne a deade man vnto lyfe of our propre ſtrenghtes, as we cal vp a man ſleapyng naturally in hys bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. But here ſpeaketh that great man, that greateſt noble Lord, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; rule death at hys pleaſure. Here ſpeaketh the creatoure and firſt maker himſelf of al thynges of hys own cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, which he made before of nothing of whome Iohn and Paule beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">Iohn. i.</note> that al thynges be made by hym, &amp; they haue there byeng by hym. But that thing was hidde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preaſtes, phariſeys &amp; the vulgar people of the Iewes at that tyme. For they knewe
<pb facs="tcp:4167:70"/>neyther Chriſt nor hys miniſtration or ſeruyce. The chief me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſynagoge ware blynd guydes, as Chriſte calleth them, neyther vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding nor bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe &amp; the Prophetes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for what might y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> miſerable poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ople, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnlerued people knowe? So it was fulfilled,
<note place="margin">Eſa. ivi and .iij.</note> that Eſaias prophecy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: al theyr blynd eſpialles was ignoraunt, the ſhepeherdes theirſelfes knewe not wyſdome. Eſa. lvi. &amp; iij. my people which cal the bleſſed, they their ſelfes deceaue the. &amp;c. But yf they had knowen &amp; lerned of the lawe, &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes two thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay of what qualite ſhould their Meſſias be, and what ſhould be his miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; work amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men in earth, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold they not haue ſcorned chriſt, but they would ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thanked him, their hartes &amp; handes lifted vp to god, becauſe thei had come to, &amp; had ſene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> quiet, ioious &amp; moſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed day; of health, in their lyfe, in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Meſſyas preſente dyd theſe ſelfe workes, which be attributed &amp; aſſigned to his firſt coming in ſcriptures, in whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che tyme he declareth alſo hym ſelf a true &amp; perfite ſauyour of our bodies &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4167:71"/>ſoules. The lawe &amp; the Prophetes tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vs firſt, that Meſſias was to come not onely a very man, but alſo a verye God, ſo that very God himſelf was to come in his own propre perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto the earth &amp; to become ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to teache and to ſaue hys people.
<note place="margin">Gene. i. Pſalm. C. xxiij. Pſalm. lxxxxvi.</note> For Moſes ſaith that God hath made heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth, whiche thing the prophetes teache alſo in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, as in <hi>123.</hi> Pſalm, God made heauen &amp; earth &amp; Pſal. <hi>96.</hi> God made heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth, &amp; all thynges whiche be in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreouer the prophetes beare witneſſe alſo, that thatſame adonay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, that true &amp; one God was to come to vs, &amp; to become a very man of the ſtocke of Dauid, that he mighte be our ſauiour &amp; Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Eſaye. xxxiij.</note> For Eſaias in the xxxiij. Chapter ſayth. Iehouah or God our iudge, God our gyuer of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, God our king: he himſelf ſhal ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs.
<note place="margin">Ieremi. xxxiij.</note> And Ier. xxxiij. where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te promyſeth Chriſt, he calleth him not onely the braunche of iuſtice, which he was to gyue to Dauid, but he calleth hym in theſame chapter clerely &amp; well to the purpoſe Iehouah, or god our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:71"/>which thing nether the Iewes nor chriſtianes may deuye, whyche hath knowen the holy tonge.</p>
               <p>Alſo in. xxij. pſalme,
<note place="margin">Pſal. xxij.</note> and in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Abdia, the kingdome is the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or gods. In bothe the places the ſpeche is of Meſſias or of Chriſte, and it calleth hym by theſame name by whiche ſcripture nameth in euery pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the trewe and onely God, maker of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, therfore it muſt nedes followe and can not be denied, that Chriſte is trew God. Is it than ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, that the creatour and maker of all thinges, reſtoreth and calleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto life his creature, now falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and deade, whiche he made before of nothing.
<note place="margin">Actu. xxvi.</note> And ſo ſaith Paule in the 26 chapter of the actes before kinge A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa, wherfor is it thought incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amonge you, if God rayſe vp dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de men, as he wold ſay. For aſmuche as ye beleue that God is almightie, &amp; that he hath made heauen and earthe, how tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may he not alſo, cal again vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lyfe his creature that is deade. Is it not more difficell and a greater thyng
<pb facs="tcp:4167:72"/>to make ſomething of nothing, than to reſtore &amp; renewe that which was made before. Whoſoeuer beleueth the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of al thinges, he muſt nedes bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue alſo that God may raiſe vp againe dead men, &amp; that he will do it, becauſe he promiſed that he him ſelfe wolde do it. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> law &amp; the prophetes tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vs, what is the miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſias, or what he hys workes which he wolde do after in earthe, that is to ſay to put away ſynnes, to ſlea death, to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power of death, to call again dead men vnto lyfe, &amp; to giue to his choſen me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting life, here for a ſhorte time to be throwen doune, to be made leſſe, &amp; to be made lowe, poore &amp; abiect, but therfore a litle after to be exalted and to reigne with his own for euer world without ende. Of theſe the Iewes might haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſothe to them ſelfes ſo great vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, if they had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heede, that they wolde not haue mocked the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Chriſt, ſaing, the whenche ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, like as he had ſpoken vaine thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and had promiſed ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:4167:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>thinges.</p>
               <p>Moſes teacheth Gene. ij.
<note place="margin">Gen. ij. Ge. iji.</note> how death came vnto the worlde by ſynne. And 3. chapter he teacheth who ſhall take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and deſtroie death, truely, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the woman, whiche ſhoulde after tread doune the head of the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the deuyll, that is to ſay to ouerthrowe &amp; deſtroie his Kingedome. The deuyll ſubdued all man kinde to him ſelfe by ſynne, that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſubiecte to death and damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<note place="margin">Heb. ij.</note> Therfore Paul ſaith in the .ij. chapter to the Hebrues, that the deuyll haith rule ouer death. The ſede of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to ſay chriſt ſhould breake and trouble this kingdome and this power of ſyune and death, holde faſte and ſlea ſynne, and kyl death.
<note place="margin">Eſai. xxxxiij.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Eſa. xxxxiij. whan Chriſt had ſaid, thou haſt made me to ſerue in thy ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> labour to me in thy iniquities, he reherſeth anone. I am, I am my ſelfe, whiche put away thy ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities for my ſake. If he putteth awai ſinne or iniquities, from whenſe death cometh, than withoute all controuerſy he putteth away death the wages of ſynne Eſa. xxv. the prophete ſayth of
<pb facs="tcp:4167:73"/>Meſſias, he ſhall throwe doune head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge,
<note place="margin">Oſee. xiij.</note> or conſume death for euer. Oſee xiij I ſhall delyuer them from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of death, I ſhall redeme them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death O death I ſhal be thy death. Eſa. ix.
<note place="margin">Eſay. ix</note> Chriſte is called the father of the world to come, or father euerlaſtingly. Therfore it is neceſſary ſuerly, that he raiſe vp his ſonnes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, &amp; graunt to them euerlaſting lyfe.
<note place="margin">Ioh. xi.</note> Therfore he ſayth in Iohn the .xi. I am the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and lyfe. Whoſoeuer beleueth on me ſhal liue, although he weredead. And whoſoeuer lyueth and beleueth in me, ſhal neuer die. And Iohn the .v. &amp; as the father rayſeth vp the dead and quicheneth them,
<note place="margin">Iohn. v.</note> euenſo the ſonne quit keneth whome he wyll.</p>
               <p>Ye ſee here of now, how great and groſſe blyndeneſſe was in Iewry, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte was ſent to them, he declareth by mightie and meruailous workes &amp; myracles that he is very Meſſias, whiche ſcripture promyſed ſauiour &amp; delyueret of the whole worlde, &amp; doith theſame ſelfe workes whiche ſcripture had prophecied Meſſias to do, &amp; wher
<pb facs="tcp:4167:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>of he might be knowen moſt playnly and moſt eaſely, but not withſtanding where he ſaith, that the wenche ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, that myſerable and blinded peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mocketh their lorde and God, but neuer the leſſe their mockinge muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſerue to faith, for by that ſelf thing they graunt that the whench is veryly deade, as alſo the ſeruauntes of the houſe of the lieuetenaunt meetinge their maiſter, ſhewe that the whench is deade, that he ſhould not offend Chriſt Therfor they myght not ſay that the whenc did lie in a traunſe or a ſwoune, or ſlaped naturally, but they doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not, and they confeſſed opnely, that ſhe had verely departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this lyfe. And therfor they ware co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to knowledge and confeſſe that a trew miracle was done here, that is to ſay, that the whench was called againe trewly from death vnto lyfe.</p>
               <p>And therfor Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth to giue to her ſome thinge, that ſhe may eat, that they ſhould not doubt that ſhe was rayſed again truly.
<note place="margin">Mat, ix</note> Matthew declared this myracle in fewe words,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>but Marc,
<note place="margin">Mare, viij. Luc, viji.</note> and Luc, adde to that anone after that Chriſt had ſaid, whenche ryſe thou vp, her ſpirite returned, &amp; ſhe dyd aryſe vp by &amp; by, &amp; that Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded meate to be giuen to her. Some me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuppoſe that that miracle which Math. declareth, where Chriſte onely raiſeth vp again the dead whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che by touching her, is an other miracle, from that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Luke &amp; Marke declare, whome they ſuppoſe to write of a whenche of ij pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res olde, the doughter of a chiefman of the ſynagoge, whoſe name was Iairus but I haue ſuppoſed hither to with En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſebius, Hierome, Auguſtine in the ij, bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of the conſent of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes the xxvi chapter, alſo with Chriſoſtome &amp; other of trew opinion &amp; faith, that theſe thre Enangeliſtes declare theſame hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory &amp; ſpeake of theſame miracle. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore our lord Ieſu Chriſte willed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his diuine power &amp; miniſtration, whan he ſaid, the whenche ſleapeth, for as Auguſtine ſaith, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can raiſe vp ſo eaſely from ſleape a man ſleapinge naturally in his bedde, how eaſely chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte raiſeth vp a deade man furth of his
<pb facs="tcp:4167:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſepulchre. And ſo wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Chriſte to ſpeake of death, as an almighty lord as lord of lyfe &amp; death, &amp; he calleth death a ſleape vnto the comfort of faithfull Chriſtians for death is made a pacified &amp; quiet ſlea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe to them that beleue in Chriſt, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be graffen in Chriſt by faith, they ſhal not ſe death, for although they ſuffer very greatly corporal death, and their ſoule departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their body, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they come not vnto the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death, which is euerlaſting da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but to Chriſt wher ther propre io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye, gladneſſe &amp; reioicinge is, &amp; the body reſteth in the earth in ſure hope of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge reſurrection, vnto the day of the lord. So ſaith alſo chriſt Iohn the xi. of Lazarus, our fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Lazarus ſleapeth, but I go that I may raiſe him vp from ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, than his diciples ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ioh. xi.</note> lord if he ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth he ſhall be ſafe, that is to ſay, he ſhall be better at eaſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their is no pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rill. But Chriſt did ſpeake of his death but they thought that he had ſpoken of the ſleaping of ſleape. Than ſaid he manyfeſtly to them, Lazarus is deade: forwhan the ſoule departeth from the body, than that departinge by it
<pb facs="tcp:4167:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelf is death, &amp; it ſhould remaine death and euerlaſtinge ſleape againſt all the power of the whole worlde, whiche might not at any tyme breake &amp; van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhe euerlaſtingly this ſleape, but whan death is compared to Chriſte, &amp; is put againſt him, than it is non other thing tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſleape to his diuine power, becauſe Chriſt (for aſmuche as he him ſelf is almighty lyfe and euerlaſtinge fontaine of al lyfe) ſpeaketh onely one word,
<note place="margin">Ioh. xi.</note> Lazarus come thou fourth. Iohn the .xi. Ionge man. I ſay to the ryſe thou vp,
<note place="margin">Luc. vij.</note> in Luke the .vij. alſo he thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the dead body, and death is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to departe, and the ſelfe lyfe to returne, as here Matthew the ix. anone after he helde the hande of the whenche,
<note place="margin">Mat. ix</note> the ſoule returneth vnto the body. For as Chriſoſtome ſaith, he put not in an other ſoule into the body, but he reſtored ſo eaſely to the body that ſelfe ſoule, whiche it had before, euen as he had rayſed it vp from ſleape. The fathers of trew faith hath wined and conſydered with muche more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, than we this diuine power of
<pb facs="tcp:4167:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt, which he hath declared in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng vp the dead by onely touchinge, and they had here very good and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry excellent meditations of the parſon of Chriſt, of the miſtery of his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, as Cyrillus vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohn in the .vi.
<note place="margin">Ioh. vi.</note> chapter, wher he ſaith, that the fleſhe of our ſauiour Chriſt is vnited or ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, alſo made lyuely to the eternal worde of God, which is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the ſelf lyfe, ſo that it may make liuely. And therfor Chriſt wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp the dead, vſed not onely words nor commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded onely, as almyghtye God, but he vſed to that buſines ſome time alſo his fleſh &amp; body, as a felowe worker that he myght declare by the ſelfe worke, that alſo hys body hath vertue of quickeninge &amp; making line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for aſmoch as it is in vnitie &amp; ioined togither to his diuine nature that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleuing, might lerne that it was his ownproper body &amp; no other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. So he raiſed vp the doughter of iairus by his worde &amp; touchinge of her body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, whiche warke was done of him whiche is God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one perſon, for he called not againe the dead vnto life
<pb facs="tcp:4167:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>alwaies by his onely word, but alſo by touchinge, that he might declare &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that his body alſo might make lyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; quicken, than for aſmuche as the thinges whiche haue bene corrupted &amp; periſhed, be reſtored, renewed &amp; begon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a freſhe, how than ſhould we not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue whiche do eate the fleſh of Chriſte? Ther is no doubte but he will bringe &amp; reforme them to perpetuall lyfe, which be partakers of him, for not onely thee ſoule muſt nedes aſcende vnto a bleſſed lyfe by the holyghoſt, but alſo this groſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe &amp; eartly body, muſt nedes be brought to a perpetuall lyfe by taſtinge, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and by meate, whichis conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and agreat to his nature, Hilarius ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth almoſt after the ſame maner of the ſe thinges alſo vpon Matthew the.
<note place="margin">Mat. ix</note> ix. chapter. And therfor the apoſtles call death a ſleape, teaching vs by this ſelfe thing, that death is to be condemned &amp; not to be feared. Luke ſaith in the .vij. of the actes,
<note place="margin">Act. vij.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Steuen ſleaped wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſtoned. Paul i. Corin. xv. nameth Chriſt the fyrſt fruites of them whiche had ſleaped,
<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note> &amp; he ſaith, we all ſhall not ſleape alſo he ſaith i. teſ. 4. brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wil
<pb facs="tcp:4167:76"/>not that ye be ignoraunt of theſe which hath ſleaped,
<note place="margin">i. Teſſa. iiij. Daniel xij.</note> that ye be not ſory &amp;c. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Dauiel hath ſpoken in the xij. after this maner of corporal death, for ſoſaith he many of them whiche ſleape in the duſt of the earth, ſhal awake, here he cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the reſurrection to come in the laſt day awakinge, all theſe forſoth be very great conſolation to all Chriſtianes, whan they be troubled with temtation of death.</p>
               <p>Now let vs heare wherfor ſcripture compareth our death to natural ſleape fyrſt whoſoeuer ſleapeth naturally, he reſteth from thoſe thoughtes and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, which he ſuffereth that watche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and he reneweth his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghtes by that reſt, whan he waketh he is not ſo wery as he was, before he did take the ſleape but quicke of ſpirite and witte, freſhe, ſtronger his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghtes being renewed, and more dilygent and ſpedy to take la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boures. So alſo our death is a reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all care, heuineſſe, thoughtes and labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res of this lyfe a litle whyle enduring, miſerable, moſt puniſhed and moſt full of aduerſitie, &amp; our body onely reſteth in the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; it ſhal returne againe
<pb facs="tcp:4167:77"/>in the laſt day renewed, ſwifte, well fortifyed, whole, mery, ſtronge, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with moſt proſperouſe and perpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall health,
<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note> as Paule teacheth vs. i. Corin. xv. The body is ſowen in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, reproche, febleneſſe &amp; is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtly body, but it riſeth again without corruption, in glory, in power, &amp; a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall body, whiche is ſo pure, ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, &amp; is preſeued ſo merualouſely of God him ſelf, that it hath nede of no meate, drinke or ſleape, &amp; that it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to no corporal febleneſſes &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as it was in this lyfe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was yet conſtrained to take meate, to drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, to ſleape, to digeſt, to ſuffre colde, heate, hungre and ſuche other things. Secondly, whoſoeuer lieng in his bed ſleapeth and reſteth naturally, he may be rayſed vp eaſely, becauſe his ſoule is in his body, &amp; the man lineth. Chriſt our God may cal againe ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely and much more eaſely deade men vnto lyfe, whoſe ſoules be not deade nor may die, Math. x. but be in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Thyroly, we go not to bedde, that we may ſleape co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually faſtened al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb facs="tcp:4167:77"/>in our bedde, but that we may reſt a fewe houres, that our body may reſtore and renewe his ſtrenghtes, &amp; that after we being wakened fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, we may do our office and duetie, &amp; that we may apply our ſtudies &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of our office. So whan we dye cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porally, our bodyes are not buried in to the earthe, that they may lie hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de perpetually in it, but they be buried that they may reſt their a certain tyme in ſure hope of reſurrection, that they may raiſe againe in the laſt day, &amp; that they may lyue togither with the ſoule euerlaſtingly, becauſe death is vtterly ouercome by Chriſte, and corporall death or ſleape is conuerted and ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned here to vs by him vnto a neceſſary and holſome medicine, that is to ſay, that ſynne and the body of ſynne may haue ſometyme their end, and that we may put awaye mortalitie by this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death, &amp; afterwarde come furth immortall at the due tyme. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Chriſt raiſeth vp alſo ſo eaſely wicked men from corporall death, as vs, not withſtandinge the death of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout and godly men is called properly
<pb facs="tcp:4167:78"/>a ſleape, and deuout and Godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſaid to ſleape onely, for whan the ſoule of a wicked or meſheuouſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the body, than nether reſt nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forting is their, for his body was the moſt filthie ſtable &amp; ſwynes ſtye of the citie Augia, yea of the deuyl, which he builded by euill thoughtes, deſyres and workes without all reſt, and is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward as a certaine abominable thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g caſt vnto the earth, tarieng that God may raiſe it vp to euerlaſtinge poniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it may be made a fyrebrande of hell, which burneth alwaies, and nut withſtanding it may not make an ende of burninge, nor be conſumed. In the meane ſeaſon the ſoule is vexed and tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled with very great tormentes &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme inquietnes, like as an euill doar worthy to be headed, whiles he ſytteth bounden in priſon &amp; cage, knowinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a very ſure rewarde or whele is at hau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, althongh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> puniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is differred a few daies, &amp; he feled it not yet in hys body, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge he is care full in minde aboue meaſure, &amp; his harte thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no other thinge than gallowes &amp; wheles, and his lyfe is no other thing, than tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blinge, terrour &amp; feare coming
<pb facs="tcp:4167:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>before the peine being at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; a moſt cruell death. Athanaſins writinge of di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe queſtions vſeth this ſymilitude, as Luke teacheth vs of the riche man lieng in tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in the .xvi. chapter,
<note place="margin">Luc. xv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and deſyreth greatly at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt his tung to be refreſhed of Lazarus, &amp; not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he coulde not receyue at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt a little droppe of water. But Lazarus had conſolation &amp; reſt in the boſome of Abraham, wher that bleſſed kepar ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riethto gither with the ſanctes vntil all the choſen be borne &amp; be called,
<note place="margin">Heb. xi.</note> for they holy fathers (as Paul ſaith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xi chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to the Hebrues) receiued not the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe, becauſe God had prouided a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain better thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for vs, that they ſhould not be made perfecte with out vs. It is plainly a contrary thing betwene them and which haue not beleued to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Ieſu chriſt, &amp; the denout &amp; Godly men, fyrſt the bodies of the deuout and godly men be ſo holy reliques, that the wicked miſheuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be vnworthy to beholde with their eyes deuout &amp; godly men, becauſe their bodies be (as Paule ſaith i. Cor. vi.)
<note place="margin">i. cor. vi.</note> membres of Chriſt and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the holi ghoſt, which duelleth in deuout &amp; godly men. And although
<pb facs="tcp:4167:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>they be buryed in the earth, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge they ſleape now in ſauing hope of reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; of that clearneſſe of whiche the ſonne is in the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they ſhall come furth of the earth and ſhalbe ioined to the bleſſed ſoules, and ſhalbe made fellowes of the celaſtyall and eternall life and ioy togither with the ſoules. This is the moſt ſure and bleſſed hope of the choſen and faithful Chriſtianes,
<note place="margin">i. Teſ. iiij.</note> as Paul teacheth. i. Teſ. iiij. If we beleue (ſaith he) that Ieſu is deade and hath riſen againe. So alſo God ſhall bringe them whiche haue ſleaped by Ieſu with him, &amp; ſo we ſhal be alwaies with him. This moſt ſure hope was ſomuch worth alwaies with deuout faithful Chriſtianes, that they did not caſte away their bodies as ſom moſt vile and naughty carion, as that ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tile Philoſopher diogenes, but they honoured it as a welbeloued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion and tellowe worker of their bleſſed ſoule and buried it honorably. And as we ſee here that a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before the houſe of this principal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſinagoge, that hys doughter bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dead, might be brought houorabely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulture, &amp; be buried.
<pb facs="tcp:4167:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>For they had hearde &amp; learned of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to haue a ſure hope, that it ſhuld be thereafter, that that ſelf body ſhuld reuiue, rayſed vp agayne in the owne tyme: for the Iewes hath the promiſe &amp; the word of God, that is to ſay, the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell of Ieſu Chriſt, whiche we haue, whiche is the promyſe of eternal lyfe.
<note place="margin">ij. tim. i</note> ij. Tim. i. Paul calleth this hope in the xxviij. of the Act. a hope of Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Actu. xxviij.</note> that is to ſay, which al true Iſraelites or de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uout Iewes loked for. And therfore they called their church yardes or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces appoyuted to the burie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes Bethhachaum, that is to ſay, the houſe of the liuing. And ſo they knewe of the worde of god, God to be God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſay, a ſauiour &amp; deliuerer of Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, &amp; Iacob, and of theirs, or theyr poſterities ſede, whiche be the faithful Chriſtian ſonnes of theſe faith ful Chriſtian Patriarches. The greke church alſo calleth the court or that pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se of ſepulchres or to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes cemiterium, that is to ſay, a place of ſleapyng, that they ſhuld not doubt that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed ſhould ſleape &amp; reſt vnto the laſte day onely, in which they ſhal aryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne
<pb facs="tcp:4167:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto euerlaſtynge lyfe.</p>
               <p>But bechaunche ſome man wil ſay, than why mock the Chriſt, if thei kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we by the word of God, that dead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould aryſe agayn? I anſwer, thei wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xe not al true Iſraelites, that is to ſay, faithfull Chiſtianes, &amp; there was yet much darkeneſſe &amp; ignoraunce with the choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyuine matters in which haue ben conuerted afterwarde. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech the at what poynt is the matters now in the churche? Suppoſe ye that thei al be true Chriſtianes which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt by name, and foloweth the bodies of dead men to be buried by cauſe of honour? how many Epicuries and Saduceis, how many ſtynkynge hogges myght thou fynde which kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp; beleue little of theſe greateſt mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters? chaffe is alwaies mixed to corne.</p>
               <p>Of theſe we lerne that churchyar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and burienges of faithful Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes ſhud be honoured and had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende dreade, for aſmuch as we wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by this ſelf thing, a Chriſtian ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of our reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for the men in our tymes be wycked and Saduceis, whiche worſhippe not fearfully the churcheyardes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes,
<pb facs="tcp:4167:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſetteth nothinge by an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſepulture, and handleth no other wyſe the bones of Chriſtianes nor ſetteth more by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than thei ware the bones of brute beaſtes. All fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtianes, as wel among the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, as the gentiles, worſhipped al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes fearefully ſepultures, as bothe the teſtamentes beareth witneſſe.</p>
               <p>Ye haue now what Chriſt meaneth here where he ſaith, the whenche ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, And what he dothe wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth her agayne vnto lyfe: whiche mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle is writen for vs, that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe, fortifie and preſerue our faith of the reſurrectïon of the body by it, for this promyſe is ſo great, by whiche Chriſte promiſeth to vs the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body, and euerlaſtyng lyfe after this lyfe, that we can not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it by reaſon, for it paſſeth al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, reaſon, and wyſedome of the whole world. Therfor oure faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deliuerer Ieſu Chriſt annexed &amp; ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth to a moſt ſure &amp; moſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſeale to this hys promyſe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he calleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn deade me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto lyfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould not doubte of this promiſe, but beleue ſtedfaſtly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as he hath called this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter
<pb facs="tcp:4167:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the man in chief auctorite, So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he ſhal rayſe vp agayne in one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente vs all in the laſte daye, not vnto a mortal lyfe, but vnto an euerlaſtyng lyfe, for as Iohn ſayth in the .v. Chapt. the houre ſhal come,
<note place="margin">Iohn. v</note> in which all men that be in ſepulchres, ſhal heare his voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, &amp; they which haue done good, ſhall come fourth vnto the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, but they which haue done euil, ſhall come fourth vnto reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. So alſo Chriſoſtome wont to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe miracles, &amp; drawe them to an Article of our faith of the myſtery of the reſurrection, that we may fortifie by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>the faith of that generall reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which ſhalbe in the later com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of chriſt, And he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vs to be of good hope and courage in the peril of death, bycauſe that our death is no more a death but a ſleap, And he ſaith that not we, but the deuill with his ſhoulde be ſorowfull and carefull or complayue. For he ſayth that we go from thys temporal life by death, vnto immortal lyfe and perpetual reſte, but that the deuyll with hys fall doune ſtrayghte vnto eternall punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4167:81"/>
               <p>Therfor whan temptations inuade vs in theſe greateſt articles, that is to ſaye, of reſurrection and lyfe to come, that they may ouerthrowe &amp; deſtroye oure faythe of the diuine promyſe to vs, than thys goſpel &amp; ſuch like, where Chriſt hath called agayne the dead vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lyfe, and by whiche he promiſeth a glorious reſurrection vnto eternal ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, is to be taken and layd hande on, &amp; our fayth ſhould be fortifyed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with theſe agaynſte the fyery dartes of the deuyll.</p>
               <p>And becauſe as Auguſtine ſayth in the C. iiij. Pſal. our faythful God hath gyuen to vs holy ſcripture hys diuyne worde, as a writynge or obligation of hys owne hand, that it myght remayn with vs, Therfor in al ſuche temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the articles of our faith, we ſhal ſhewe forth anone the very propre obli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of God, &amp; we ſhal beholde hys mercy &amp; veritie in it. Yf Satan te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth vs, putting voluptuous thoughtes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hartes, as yf god wold ſuffre vs to peryſh by death, &amp; as yf we ſhoulde remayn vnder the earth, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs take quickely his hand writtyng, the holye
<pb facs="tcp:4167:82"/>guſpel, &amp; let vs ſee what God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſeth to vs, what now he hath done &amp; gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſhall gyue yet. He hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſurely to vs his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne vnto a ſauinur.
<note place="margin">Nota be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> He hath ſent him in ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of tyme. He hath ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhuld dye for vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath ben done. He ſaid that he ſhould ryſe agayn &amp; aſee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo it came to paſſe. He ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he wolde ſend his holy ghoſt for erneſt money of the celeſtial heritage, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alſo was done, He promyſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he wold publiſhe abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the goſpel, throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole world &amp; cal the gentiles to euerlaſtyng lyfe. Hè dyd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo, he promiſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde ſaue &amp; defend hys welbeloued people, faithful chriſtianes, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world among ſo many deuils &amp; impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may perſeuer &amp; abyde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende. He did y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo. See thou his hand writing, &amp; loke thou what he oweth moreouer. He ſhal come vnto iudgement, he ſhall rayſe vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea &amp; earthe, all dead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the laſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhal leade good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his king do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhal thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte doune euil me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helles vnto euer laſting tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſhed al thynges, which he promiſed
<pb facs="tcp:4167:82"/>to vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obligation of his hand writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge. Therfor for as muche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt true god, &amp; celeſtial father hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed &amp; paied al thiges with ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his promiſe, as we kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp; confeſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherfor ſhoulde we doubte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is, of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſurrection, &amp; of the bleſſyng to come? O vnthan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefull man. Thou readeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dette, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> feaſt what is payed, wherfor doubteſt thou, but alſo he will performe &amp; pay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſte? By what faythful execution of promyſe he hath payed thoſe thinges, which we haue receyued now, by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame faithful executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of promyſe, he wil pay thoſe thynges which reſt &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, &amp; he ſhal rayſe vs vp agayne, &amp; he wil tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſfigure our bodyes, which be now vyle, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke to hys gloriouſe body, in effect or vertue, by which it may alſo make ſubiect to it ſelf al thynges. Phil. iij.
<note place="margin">Phil. iij</note> Theſe be ſayd of this goſpel. Chriſt our Lord &amp; God voucheſafe to fortifye our faith, that we neuer doubte of the moſte ſure veritie of hys promyſe. AMEN.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Seke peace, and enſue it.
<bibl>Pſalm. xxxiij. i. Pet. iij.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Walter Lynne</figDesc>
                  <p>W L</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted for Gwalter Lynne, dwellyng vpon So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers kaye, by Byllynges gate. In the yeare of our Lorde God. M.D.xiviij.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4167:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
